This meeting is being recorded.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen. I'd
like to call the February 9th meeting of
the governing body to order. It is very
nice to see so many people in our
audience. So, thanks for being here this
evening. Madame Clerk, would you please
take the role?
>> Mr. Crave,
>> present.
>> Mr. White,
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> here.
>> Dr. Mr. Aldrich,
>> Mayor Collins
>> here,
>> Dr. Emmens
>> present.
>> Mr. Esel
>> here.
>> Mr. Lebornne
>> Mr. Moody
>> present.
>> Dr. Renie
>> All members are present. We do have a
quorum.
>> Will you please join me in the pledge of
allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Consent agenda. All agenda items listed
with the designation of CA are
considered to be routine items by the
governing body and will be enacted by
one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body so requests
and support by two other members is
received. Any item removed from the
consent agenda will be considered in its
normal sequence on the agenda.
>> All right. Are there any items a member
of the governing body would like to
remove from the consent agenda?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> 21A.
Concur.
>> Concur.
>> Uh, and also um 21 C.
>> All right. We have 21 A and 21 C
removed. Is there anyone else hearing?
None. I would uh entertain a motion,
please.
>> So moved.
>> Second.
>> Moved by Mr. White and seconded by Mr.
Crave. All those in favor of the consent
agenda with 21 A and C removed, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. Those opposed.
>> The consent agenda is approved.
>> Number 7A, public hearing to determine
whether compliance of annexation
conditions required by Wyoming statute
15-1-402
exists for the city initiated annexation
of 16 parcels of land totaling roughly
49.4 4 acres comprised of various tracks
of land. Situate in western and southern
Cheyenne generally located east of I25
south of the intersection of Westland
Road and Missile Drive north of West and
East Allison Road and east of and
adjacent to North College Drive.
>> All right, before we get started on
this, I see a lot of new faces and I'm
thinking many of you may have come today
to uh testify under this public hearing
and we're excited that you're here. Um
if you not been here before, maybe I
thought just go through how we do this.
Okay, we have a podium on either side of
the room. Um, when you get up there,
you'll have a threeminut limit to be
able to talk and if you just please
clearly identify your name for the
record so we can do that and we look
forward to having your testimony. Okay.
Uh, when you get up there, you'll have
to push that button and you'll see the
light underneath here turn on and that
way you'll know the microphone is on.
And it's very difficult for people
sitting in that part of the building or
for people online to hear if you don't
bring the microphone right up to your
face. So about two inches from your
mouth really helps make that more clear.
So if you do that for us, we'd really
appreciate it and we'll look forward to
that. And before we get started, we'll
start with a staff report. Mr. White,
mayor, and members of council, Conor Way
Planning and Development Department.
Uh the sanctation is for 16 parcels of
land totaling roughly 49.4 for acres
generally located east of I25, south of
um south of the intersection of Westland
Road and Missile Drive, north of West
and East Allison Road, and east of and
adjacent to North College Drive.
This is a city initiated annexation
pursuant to Wyoming State Statute
15-1-404.
Resolution initiating this annexation
was adopted by the governing body on
January 26 uh 2026.
This public hearing is being held in
accordance with Wyoming state statute
15-1-402A.
Pursent to fulfilling uh the
requirements of state statute staff asks
asks the governing body to consider the
following. The land proposed to be
annexed is contiguous to current city
limits. Specifically, the parcels are
100% contiguous.
All city services and utilities
currently available to residents of the
city will be provided to residents of
the annex land. Extending water and
sewer will increase the health safety of
the residents living in this area of the
community. The the area to be annexed is
inside the urban service boundary and it
is designated uh with mixed use
employment, mixed or urban residential
and mixed use residential by the future
land use map.
Uh this type of development is best
supported by being within city limits
and connecting to city services.
Certified mailing was sent to all land
owners and utilities within the annexed
area not less than 20 business days
prior to the public hearing. According
to the calendar, 20 business days prior
to today's hearing was January 9th. The
certified mailing was sent out on
January 8th. The earliest confirmed
receipt was January 12th. and property
owners within 300 ft of the subject
properties were also mailed notice in
that same time period.
The sanctation is also accompanied by an
assigned zoning ordinance.
Uh a couple additional information um
points that I'll have. Uh on December
16th, 2025, myself and fire chief Dy
Shorn hosted a county pocket Q&A meeting
uh for property owners within the um
proposed pocket annexation. Uh, one
property owner showed up to that
meeting.
Staff has received comment from three
property owners within this ann uh
within this annexation. Two of the
property owners uh do not have any
concerns with the annexation. Uh the
third has a list of concerns and the
property in question is parcel 4 which
is the farm and farm stand on
Waltershide. Uh answers to many of the
concerns have been um answered within
the council packet which is an
attachment for item 15 on tonight's
agenda. I would like to make one note um
which is a correction for some of those
uh for one of those um questions in
there. The annual property tax will only
increase about $90 not as not what is
listed within that um packet.
One of the concerns I would like to
address that our office has had several
comments about is the continued
operation of the farm and farm stand. Uh
per state statute, land uses such as the
farm and farm stand are required to be
allowed to continue uh when the city
initiates annexation.
In addition, staff is proposing the AG
agricultural zone with the assigned
zoning ordinance, which is item number
16 on tonight's agenda as well. Uh the
AG zone would allow the farm to be a use
by right and it would allow the farm uh
stand to be a permitted use. Adjustments
to animal numbers uh within existing
pastures do not require approval and can
continue.
With that I do stand for any questions.
>> Mr. White. Thank you. Uh questions for
Connor.
>> Dr. Ems, did you have a question?
>> No. Oh, sorry.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Uh
thank you, Mr. White. Uh let's say uh
parcel 4 wants to expand in the future.
Um what would they have to do exactly?
If you can uh inform the public what
would they have to do if they want to
expand? Mayor through you. So expansion
um because it is a permitted use. We'd
look at what that expansion is. If it's
adding a structure, there would be
building permit requirements. Um
depending on the expansion, there might
be a site plan that's required just to
notate what the expansion is. Um but
that would be the extent of what the
expansion would be. Follow
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor Thuru. And thank
you for that answer. What would be the
approximate cost low end to the high
end?
>> Mr. Mayor through you. I'm not sure what
a building permit would cost. It's based
on evaluation of work. Um a minor site
plan adjustment is a $100 application.
>> Thank you.
>> Is that for Dr. Aldridge? Dr. Aldridge.
Good evening, Mayor Collins through you.
Um I am just wondering about the state
statute um that um Connor you just
mentioned. Uh the state statute that
allows the farming to continue. Um it
doesn't it in the state statute does it
have anything that talks about the if
they should want to expand or add
animals or does that change any of the
considerations for how we've been doing
these annexations?
>> I can I could read the statute if if
that would help.
>> Mr. Mayor, I can also add that yes, the
state statute does state that basically
any any use when the city annexes um is
basically a grandfathered use. That's
why I did want to mention that staff is
recommending the AG zone, which makes it
a use by right and a permitted use. So,
with it being a use by right and
permitted use, they're allowed that
expansion, allowed the increase in
animals just by the zoning code itself
rather than the state statute.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, thank you very much
through you. Uh, Mr. one, I'd like to
take you through a series of questions.
Um, if the mayor will permit it. Um,
first of all, what's right across
Waltershide, uh, to the east of this
property? That is this is the lot for
that we're talking about.
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, through you. Uh, to the
east would be an apartment complex as
well as I believe there's a school, the
Boys and Girls Club, maybe a daycare on
that side of the
>> Head Start.
>> Head Start. Right.
There's a daycare there uh as well as uh
a lot of apartments. Now, what about to
the north end uh on the uh east side of
Waltershide? What's what's up there
>> on the You mean
>> if you go if you go north on Walters and
>> on the east side or
>> on the east on the east side
>> that
>> there's a big mo there's a big motel
there, isn't there? I
>> believe so. Yes.
>> Okay. And just north of this property on
uh the same side of the street that they
are on, what's there?
>> Uh all of that, mayor through you, all
of that is single family housing.
>> And to the west of this property, what's
there?
>> Uh single family housing as well.
>> And what's on the south of this
property?
>> That I believe is an electrical
ser or basically a service station for
just the power grid
>> substation.
>> Substation. Well, and in point of fact,
there are aren't there there are two WA
high voltage transmission lines, one on
the north and one on the south,
>> Mr. Mayor, through you. That is correct.
>> Okay. And um isn't the greenway come
down on the south side of this property?
>> Mayor, through you that is also correct.
>> Thank you. Um what's your understanding
about how
the property owners, Mr. Mrs. nicely.
Current h current currently handle
predators uh that um may be uh affecting
their um their livestock.
>> Mr. Mayor, through you my understanding
is they do shoot the predators. Uh so
they do use firearms to kill those
predators.
>> Okay. And and these are high-powered
rifles to shoot what kind of predators,
>> Mr. Mayor. I'm not sure what types of
weapons. Um, probably foxes,
maybe. I've heard coyotes. Those would
be the two.
>> Okay.
>> Raccoons.
>> Mr. Wolf, I've been told it's a 12 gauge
shotgun with number eight shot.
>> Okay.
Thank you. Um, and what would they be
permitted to do uh once this land uh if
the land is annexed?
>> Mr. Mayor, through you. My understanding
is firearms are not allowed to be
discharged within city limits.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Thank you,
Mr. White.
>> Ladies and gentlemen, we have a bunch of
chairs still here and I see a lot of
people standing. Um, you know, please
make yourself home. We're going to be
here for a while tonight, I think. So,
uh, don't be shy. Just come on in. Think
of it like church. We all like each
other and we'll just find a place for
everybody. Okay.
>> Any other questions for Mr. White?
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Uh, thank
you, sir. Have there been any reports
that you can think of where they're
discharging just a regular shotgun with
these predators at all? Any complaints?
Any police reports from the motel or
property owners surrounding them?
>> Mr. Mayor, through you. I'm not aware of
anything. I did not research or dive
into that.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you through you. U Mr.
Connor, how long have you been talking
with Mr. Mrs. nicely about the proposed
annexation.
>> Mr. Mayor, through you. My understanding
is my director uh director Bloom has had
email contacts with Mr. Nicely since
July of 22. Um on December 16th, that
meeting I had mentioned, that was also a
meeting where Mr. Nicely and Mrs. Nicely
attended that meeting. Uh so they were
the only property owner that was there
and then we've had contact the past
couple weeks. So you've you've been
involved in in this proposed annexation
of this property now for three years,
three and a half years,
>> Mr. Mayor. Three roughly three to four.
>> Okay. And and within the last uh month
or so, you've had uh obviously a number
of conversations with the nicely and
exchanges of emails.
>> Mr. Mayor, through you there have been
email exchanges, not specifically with
me. and I have been on those chains but
with Director Bloom and others.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Thank you, Mr.
White.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> All right, Connor, thanks for being here
tonight. All right, this is your
opportunity if you want to come up and
address the governing body. Uh we have a
u uh a public hearing. Uh we we'll try
to limit our comments if we can to three
minutes and we would uh appreciate it if
uh you all come and talk to us.
Good evening,
>> David. Remember, you got to push that
button.
>> There you go.
>> Oh, I don't hold it.
>> No,
>> we got you though. David Nisley 200
Waltersite.
>> Members of the council, thank you for
being here. Uh, thank you for your
interaction with me. Those of you who
have interacted with me, thank you, Mr.
Mayor, um, for a conversation even today
and over the weekend. And thank you for
working
on our behalf. Um, thank you to
planning. Um, thank you to all those
wearing green and those who are
supporting us who don't wear green. Um,
I'm here tonight to say, um, to all of
you,
let's be kind.
Let's be respectful.
Um, I'm here as a a follower of Jesus to
try to do what he'd have me to do and
and that's be kind and respectful. Mr.
Esabel, one of your your brother Floyd
is one of my heroes. Um he was always
kind and respectful. Um and and and I
appreciate him for that and I I trust
you are too. Um I've had interactions
with um the Laram County Sheriff's
Department and reported to them that I
had shot um predators who were attacking
our livestock
over the course of the years. Um, I've
been assured by the sheriff's department
and by animal control that number eight
shot in a shotgun at short range is
acceptable and appropriate and
justifiable.
Um, I have
reported that to the city police who've
been called uh because they've heard it
and they assured me that it was within
not only our rights but safety. Um,
we're careful not to endanger the
public.
We have had conversations. I brought it
to to the uh tension of planning for
three and a half years. Um, that we're a
farm with a big vision.
um and that we won't continue to only do
what we've been doing, but we expect to
grow and expand
because that's the nature of farming and
because the city of Cheyenne needs
healthy food and healthy access to food.
Um my wife will tell you more about her
big vision because she's the big
visionary behind it. And you won't find
a smarter, more beautiful person, but I
can't find her.
>> She's right here. There she is.
[laughter] I I thought she finally left
me.
Um, so what I'm here to ask you tonight
is the kindness
because we didn't get notice until
January 27th. The post office didn't
deliver it. It was marked no such number
and returned to planning on the 27th of
January, less than two weeks ago. We got
an email from planning.
State legislaturator's intention is that
we get notice mailed and received 20
days in advance.
So give us a chance to work it out. Um
just this weekend I've been having
conversations
about working it out and coming to some
conclusion.
I've been assured by the mayor's office
that we have legitimate concerns.
It's being reserved in the packet. We
have concerns that are bothersome to us,
but let's work it out. Let's give us
time to work it out.
I hope someone will make a motion and
you all will support it to postpone this
action
so that we can come to some
understanding. Just today questions were
asked and the answers weren't known.
For three and a half years I've asked
questions like
how will we protect livestock or what
happens if we expand and the answers
haven't been received.
So please let's work it out. Let's be
kind. Let's be respectful.
What's the hurry?
Why rush things?
I believe we can be a great positive
force for the city of Cheyenne.
I believe that the city of Cheyenne in
partnership with us
could have a beautiful relationship, but
we haven't started out that way.
Um, I don't understand why. Maybe it's
me,
maybe it's not.
I'm sure at least in part it is me. But
um I'm learning and I'm growing and I'm
willing to learn and grow. Um let's be
kind.
Let's be respectful.
Thank you.
>> Thanks for being here. David Tommy, you
might as well come up.
>> And do I have to?
>> Nope. It's on.
>> It's already on. Okay. Sorry. I'm Tommy
Nicely. I'm the owner of WFresh Farm at
200 Walterside Boulevard and I am asking
you to postpone the annexation of my
farm.
I'm being told that if I think and
behave small that nothing will change.
The problem is I have big plans.
I am convinced by the documentation of
your very own agenda and with the
correspondences with city officials that
anything more than small minuscule
changes could
and probably would trigger the
requirement to bring Waltershide
Boulevard and Dur Avenue up to city code
requirements. That would require curbs,
gutters, and sidewalk for over 1,600
feet. That would cost me hundreds and
thousands of dollars. I cannot bear that
cost.
Furthermore, our livestock will be
unprotected due to current city codes.
These are just two possible consequences
of annexation.
There are many others.
Please don't endanger my farm.
It's not too late to do better,
Cheyenne. Please postpone.
>> Tommy, it's nice to have you here
tonight. Thank you.
All right, push that button till the
light turns green.
>> See if I'm close enough.
>> Perfect.
>> Hi, my name is Chelsea Hacker McCord. I
live here um couple blocks away from
this place. Um, I would also like to
speak regarding parcel 4, Yfresh. Um,
first of all, I'd like to thank you city
council members and mayor for allowing
us to be able to voice our opinions to
the public. Um, I think that staying
annexation or not annexing at all needs
to happen in regards to Wresh. Um, I'm
speaking before you today in three
capacities. Uh, I am a member of the
public as I stated. Um, I am a small
business owner myself who sells through
WFresh and I am also a friend of the
nicely. I have been actively involved
recently with helping raise awareness
regarding this issue. So, I'm instantly
I have intimate knowledge regarding a
lot of the nuances that may have been
misconstrued or confused. Okay. To
begin, I want to be clear that Wirefresh
understands that the annexation and
zoning of agg will not initially cause
them to stop farming, raising livestock
or operating the farm stand. The harm
comes through the unclear, unwritten
city codes and ordinances. The effect on
Wfresh will not immediately show up. Um,
the simplest solution to all of this is
to just not annex Wresh. I do however
know and can understand that the city
wishes for annexation. If that is the
case, I must ask you to please stay it
for the time being until all the issues
have been fully resolved and documented.
To illustrate this, I will address two
different um specifics. First of all, I
would like to address how I believe that
complete answers haven't been given and
how those answers that have been getting
many of those answers are in congruent
with how urban agriculture works. Okay,
I don't have very long at the end of my
a lot of time. If I am unclear, please
ask and I would love to clarify. Um to
begin, number one, many of the answers
that are given are incomplete. There is
a generic statement providing no further
clarification and then directing Yfresh
to obtain additional information from
another department. For instance,
regarding farmstand licensings, the
planning department has said that there
is a $75 fee of their license. This is
helpful. And that WFresh will still need
to comply with public health
requirements. Great. And what are those?
Rather than uh providing those
requirements specifically, WFresh has
been directed to contact a different
department to quote obtain further
information. Although not their preview,
there was no verification by the
responder that the further information
was indeed given. I remind you it is the
city that is pushing this annexation.
Furthermore, the city intends to annex
still um the land regardless if answers
are given or not. Um, I feel like the
city should at least verify that all
questions and impacts have been conveyed
to WFresh before proceeding with the
annexation.
Um, let me quickly reverse the roles for
a minute. If developer wants to come in
and build something within the city, you
guys would obviously have questions um,
in order to evaluate and weigh all of
the impacts. The developer would answer
some questions, but for some of them,
they might just simply answer, "Please
call this other person to obtain
additional information." Imagine that
developer proceeds to build this
building without the questions being
answered, studies or plans being
provided, or meeting additional
requirements. Basically, we don't care
if you know, we're just going to do it
anyways. Please provide WFresh with the
same respect that you guys ask of the
city. Um,
>> ma'am, and ladies and gentlemen, I
appreciate that you feel really
passionately about this, but we're going
to be very quiet and just listen to the
folks. It's my job to try to keep order
and if we start talking like that then
it gets out of control. So thank you
very much. I appreciate that you agree
but let's not do that tonight. Okay.
Thank you.
>> Okay. Due to time I won't be able to
touch on the second point that I wish to
address um unless you would like me to
elaborate more but my conclusion
basically is that this is not an
unsolvable problem. Many other cities
have developed policies when
encountering similar issues when
incorporating urban.
>> Thank you very much. Thank you.
Appreciate you being here this evening.
>> Yes.
>> Thank you.
Sheriff, welcome.
>> How are you?
>> Okay,
>> go [clears throat] ahead.
>> U, so thank you, Mayor Collins and
members of the council. So, I'm Brian
Kak, your sheriff, and I was asked to
comment briefly on our mutual aid
contract that we have in place with the
police department because I know it's
been a topic um reference um this agenda
item about consistency of law
enforcement services. And so we have
this mutual aid contract that um I allow
the police officers to have full
authority in the unincorporated areas of
the county. So in other words, if you
wanted to keep this as a county pocket,
uh we could easily set it up so that
your officers would be the primary
agency to respond to calls there. So I
just wanted to throw that out there um
so that you are aware of the the
agreement that we have. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Thanks for your service.
>> Sure thing.
>> Appreciate it. Yes, ma'am.
Good evening, Mr. Mayor. I'm sorry, I'm
got a cold. Tamara Trill, Ward One.
Sorry about that. So, I wasn't going to
speak tonight, but I I feel like I need
a quick remind to remind everybody that
this happened, this subject of annexing
the farm stand happened when you guys
started bringing the data centers and
you started wanting to annex all of
Southside
and we tried at a state level. Even even
Representative Berlingame, it was her
issue. Then it went to Representative
Styiver and myself.
Everybody is against this. And we tried
to change it at the state level so the
city would have less control and less
ability to do such things. But we didn't
because we're leaving it to local
control because they know better of what
their people want. you're not listening
at all.
So maybe we do need to take it back to
the state level.
That's all I got to say.
>> Hello, sir. Welcome.
>> Salve. My name is Richard. I am the
almost 14-year-old son of Tommy and
David Nicely.
A Babylonian king. I once built seven
layered palace and it was a big green
space just to impress his wife.
I am here to say that do not think of
urban farms or what by farm as a greed
as a undeveloped great spotted giant
which is but think of it as a marriage
gift to Cheyenne.
Virgil, the Roman epic poet, once said
that he preferred his bees
than to writing epic poetry.
If that is the case,
then why should not we bring agriculture
horiculture and edible husbandry to a
city?
As we have seen in 1900
about half the population of the states
was urban and half of it was
agriculture. By the '9s 75% was urban
while
only about 30% was agriculture.
By now it is even lower.
We have an ability here
to make an example of Cheyenne
to bring agriculture
to the cities
and we bring the cities to agriculture.
This will bring agricultural benefits
such as people knowing where their food
comes from. giving people more choice
about their food while also bringing
urban benefits to agriculture
such as more more entertainment, more
abilities for kids to get an education,
more
this
is I believe
will
help make America a better society.
As we have seen within the last few
presidential elections, we are already a
divided country.
If we bring people of different jobs and
different backgrounds together, we can
serve to unify a country.
That is all I have to say.
>> Richard, thanks for being here. You did
a nice job.
[applause]
>> Kathy, welcome.
Good evening, Mayor and Council. Kathy
Sigliano. I am speaking today as a
Cheyenne resident who is incredibly
frustrated by the proposed forced
annexation of Wresh,
a small local farm stand that has become
a meaningful part of our community.
What's more concerning is not the
annexation itself, but the way the
questions from the public and the
business owners have been handled. When
residents seek clarity, we're told that
we are getting misinformation
or that some of the officials are
confused because they thought that the
the owners understood what was going on.
From where many of us are sitting, there
has been very little misinformation
coming from the public. The confusion
appears to be coming from the city and
even council members that have admitted
that they can't seem to get consistent
answers themselves. That should be a red
flag. We also heard a council member
tell this business that he believes
freedom is a form of selfishness for a
small local operation simply trying to
grow food and serve its neighbors. That
kind of statement is unacceptable. Small
businesses are not the enemy. They are
the backbone of our community.
There are still too many unanswered
questions about costs, requirements,
timelines, and long-term impacts.
Rushing forward without clear,
consistent information only erodess
public trust. I urge you to slow the
process down and take time to sit down
with wfresh owners along with
appropriate department heads to work
through real solutions. Figure out how
this business can continue to operate
and thrive without being forced into
thousands of dollars in expenses for
something they are not asking for.
Cheyenne should be a place where local
agriculture and small business are
supported, not steamrolled by process
and confusion. Please take your time and
get this right. Thank you.
>> Miss McCoy.
>> Good evening, mayor, members of the
council. My name is Patricia McCoy and I
live on the south side. These are my
neighbors.
I shop their farm stand often. for my
eggs,
my milk, my honey, my herbs. I would
much rather shop from them and know
exactly where my stuff comes from rather
than going to a big box store and trying
to look at a label to see how many
chemicals they have put in it. For
years, my family has relied on this farm
stand. We aren't just customers. We're a
community.
We value knowing exactly where our food
comes from. And it's not just about my
generation's habits.
When my 22-year-old daughter heard this
stand was facing annexation and being
met with vague answers from the city,
she was devastated and she was angry.
She didn't just sit by. She took to
social media, posting a photo of herself
with her local milk and her local eggs
from her favorite farm stand.
She called on all of her peers to stand
up and tell you no, to save her farm
stand that she likes to shop at. The
outpouring of support she received
proves one thing. The younger generation
in Cheyenne wants this. They want
sustainability. They want local
entrepreneurship and they want the
southside to keep its unique character.
They are watching how this city treats
its small producers. The fear here is
that annexation will bring a wave of
city standard red tape and
infrastructure costs that a small
agricultural operation simply cannot
absorb. If you force this stand to come
to code like a big box retailer, you
aren't improving our neighborhood. We
know there's hotels there. We know
there's apartments there. We didn't want
those either. But you didn't listen
then. You don't listen now.
This is our neighborhood and our food.
We know where it comes from. We know who
grows it. And we want to keep it that
way. So, I would beg you, not ask you to
postpone this. Give us the answers that
we're asking for. Let our farm be as it
is and let it continue to grow and
thrive. that will enrich our community.
Thank you,
>> guys.
Please, now let's not do that. I don't
want to have to clear the room. Please.
Thank you very much. Don, welcome. My
name is Don Edmonds. I'm at 7309 East
Persian Boulevard. I've been to a number
of these meetings and I have seen just
about every one of them that you have
groups of people come in here and object
to being annexed. Well, the thing about
it is I applaud everybody here that's
here tonight in this annexation, but the
problem about it is I blame this problem
on the city council and the city
government.
>> Bring that microphone up and talk into
the microphone.
>> I blame this problem on the council and
the city government because you annex
property willy-nilly. Uh you create
county pockets.
I live out on the east side of town. We
are so terrified out there. I live on uh
Persian Boulevard on the south side.
Well, I've got a city uh arm sticking
out called Saddle Ridge out to Christen
Road. I have another one going on the UP
Railroad way east. And unfortunately, or
lucky for us, Christen Road is not city
yet. But if it does get into the city,
you're going to have a huge city pocket.
So, that's why we're fighting on having
Christen Road not become county uh city
prop uh street or anything. But the
thing is, I think the city needs to look
into it. And when you do an annexation,
are you going to create a possible
county pocket by doing an annexation? I
think you need to look at this because
it's quite uh it's quite costly to the
people that you annex. If you want to
annex these properties so bad, you take
care of all the fees, all the
construction, and everything else that's
required to bring these uh properties
into compliance with the city ordinance.
because when the people moved out there
like myself, I've lived out at my
property since 1956. That's when my
father bought the property and I bought
it from him and I was way out in the
county. Way out in the county. Now the
county is right next door to or the
city's right next door to me. And I find
that kind of scary because we have
people that are coming in from the city,
especially Saddle Ridge, that are not
nice people. They are not nice drivers.
We've had deaths at US uh 30 and Whitney
because the thing is is people are in a
hurry and they don't wait didn't wait
for traffic. So it cost a lot of money
to fix those intersections and now
there's another one coming up at Dell
Range. That's going to be ridiculous
putting them below a crest of a hill.
But the thing about it is you folks
really need to look at what you're
annexing and if it's going to create a
city pocket, take a gander at it. Is it
worth it? Is it worth it to annex it in
or to tell whoever wants that property
that they want in the city? Tell them
no. I think that would be a simple
solution.
>> Don, thanks. Good to see you. Hi, ma'am.
How are you this evening?
>> Very fine. Uh, Mr. Mayor, council
members, uh,
>> my name is Francine Sheiel and I also
live on the south side and I also am a
customer of the Little Wyoming Farm
Stand, a small family-owned business for
well over a year. The first thing I
noticed when I walked in there was they
presented their products. There was a
sign there that said, "This is homemade.
This is not certified, labeled,
licensed, packaged, or regulated."
inspected. All of us who choose to shop
at this little farm stand are well aware
of what what that sign means. And we
choose to shop there. We choose to eat
more naturally, more pure foods as the
rest of them think.
Sorry, I lost my train of thought.
>> Just take your time. You're fine.
This this farm stand provides good
Wyoming beef, cow's milk, goat milk,
yogurt, cheese, jams, eggs. Oh, and
about that, uh, chickens uh, don't
wander around at night. Chickens go to
roost. I have chickens. They go to bed
at sundown. They're not wandering around
and and annoying anyone.
You folks say you support small business
here in Wyoming. If you overregulate
this small farm business, you will also
be harming the good people who bring
their products to sell at this farm
stand. There are also small family farms
just trying to get by.
You are also asking this lady to give up
her home of 19 years. How many of you
would not raise a fuss if someone tried
to do that to you and your homes?
Surely in your wisdom and benevolence,
you can find a way to grant these folks
an ability to earn their living and also
the other small farms who supply
products without them overregulating
this business.
Perhaps you should come out, see what
that we're trying to protect,
perhaps even try some of the products. I
thank you,
>> Francine. I had glad that you're here
tonight, but I will share with you. Hey
guys, please.
There is nobody on this governing body
that wants to put them out of business.
Please. Who's next?
Welcome, ma'am.
I got to turn it back on. There you go.
>> My name is Roxy Hobble and I
>> Roxy, can you bring that up a little
bit? Good.
>> My name is Roxy Havl and I live on track
7 that you guys are trying to um annex.
Um we just live over where there is
nobody around us and we got a letter
back in January saying that you're going
to annex us um because we are a pocket.
But I just want you guys to know that
there is absolutely no pocket around us.
Um we live on the um east side of
college. We own um one of the very first
dairy farms um or dairy barns that was
here in Cheyenne. We are trying to
restore that barn. We do have animals,
horses um um and we're just uh I just
wanted you guys to know that there is
more people than the one Wyoming um that
we are not for this annexing. Um for
one, it says in this letter that you
guys um the sewer and um the water. I
just want you guys to know about a year
ago we've paid almost $30,000 to have a
well installed um on this on our
property. So if we annex into you guys
is we now have a bill and then what do I
do with that $30,000 well?
>> Roxy, let me answer that question for
you just directly. Okay. When we very
first started this process back in 2022,
we recognized that, you know, there
there would be expenses that could
happen. And so we went we spent a year
working on trying to change our
ordinances so that um we could mitigate
as much of that as possible. So when
your property is annexed, you do not
have to hook on to city water and you
don't have to hook on to city sewer. But
if you want to, you have access to it
because now you're a city resident. So
if you have a beautiful $30,000 well and
it's working properly, you get to use
that. No problem at all. We have no
problem with that.
>> But once it goes down, what do we do
then? Well, that would be between you
and and the the health department. If
you have enough land, you know, to
expand it and you can get a 21
exception, then you might be able to uh
to fix that. Um I I think really the
challenge is more on the sewer side that
the septic systems for most people. We
haven't really had a lot of problems
with people being able to get their
their wells repaired. Um so we looked at
that. We have no requirement that you
have to hook up or install curb gutter,
sidewalk, fix the roads. Uh fact of the
matter is we don't ask you to do
anything. Um except to be fair um you
have to change over to our our
sanitation department. Um we have a
monopoly on on garbage pickup. So you'll
honestly that's one thing. There will be
a small difference in the property taxes
in uh David and uh Tommy's property. Uh
we learned it's about $90 a year
additional property taxes. Um, and you
know, so we we recognized that if we're
going to annex all the county pockets in
Cheyenne, we wanted to make sure that
there was not a lot of um expenses that
would go to the owner. Before that, when
we when you came in, you had to bring
your property up to city standards, but
we realized that wouldn't be fair. And
so if you were to um u you know change
the use or you know do some things like
that just as in the county there may be
some off-site improvements that you
would have to do but that would be
because you chose to do something
different not because you're just moving
into that place. I took some of your
time so please continue.
>> Yeah. I I mean I wasn't going to speak
tonight, but um I just wanted to let you
guys know that we're not for this
annexing. Um because we bought this
well, we bought the farm to have our
horses and everything and it is on the
outskirts of the city. There is
absolutely nothing that's city around us
whatsoever. And so I just wanted to let
you know that that that there is more
families in this town that are not for
this annexation. Rox and Roxy, I think
it's important for you and for um you
know, everybody that's here to
understand there is a state law um it's
subsection A that says when the city
initiates an annexation that your
continued uses of that property are
protected not only for you but also for
the successors that would be on that
property. So if you have horses on there
and you're doing the agriculture uses
just because you are coming into the
city means you get to keep those uses.
Um, that also says though, if you don't
do it for a year, you might lose that.
So, you got to make sure it's continuous
use. So, anything you did uh in in the
previous year beforehand, those things
are are grandfathered. So, in the case
of David and Tommy, they're they're a
farm. They'll the state law says they
get to be a farm. Um, in your case, you
have a barn and you're going to have
some horses or cow or whatever that you
have there. The state law says you get
to continue to do that. And the way that
we want to make sure of that is because
I'm not going to be here in five years.
our planning department might not be
here, the employees. We uh we uh we fill
out a form that talks about what those
continuing uses are so that we can put
it in the record so that when we're all
gone and somebody says, "Well, how come
you have a cow? You can't have a cow in
the city limits." We have a we have
something we go back to and says, "Oh,
but they had a cow when we annexed
them." So, they get to they had a horse.
They have chickens. You know, whatever
that non-conforming use might be um that
that protects that for you. And that's
not a city rule. That's a state law that
protects the people uh who are annexed
against their when the city initiates
initiates an annexation. If you were to
annex your property, then you'd have to
meet all the things because you're
asking to come in. But because it goes
the other way, then we have to make sure
that we try to protect you and the state
law makes us do that. And so it's really
important that as we go through this
process that we write down and
understand what is it you do with your
property so that we can make sure we
protect those into the future.
>> Does that make sense?
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you.
Thank you,
>> sir.
You're here a lot, but I don't think
I've ever seen you talk before. Welcome.
>> Hi, I'm Richard Lyle. I'm speaking for
myself. Um, I think that in Cheyenne,
uh, you know, with all due respect to
Albertson's,
uh, King Supers and Walmart and the
other corporate grocery stores, we need
a retailer here who will sell locally
produced vegetables and lo locally
sourced uh, meat and other uh, products
in the United states right now um the
meat processing is controlled by total
of four corporations control 85% of the
meat two of those four corporations are
not based in the United States
u
uh chi a Chinese uh body bought
Smithfield uh you know um and I don't
like our food supply being controlled
uh elsewhere.
And so I would urge that you not enact
any regulations
that would impede a small family farm.
And thank you very much. I yield my time
back to the
I have to tell you guys, I see Richard
at the gym a lot and when he's doing his
chin-ups
It's pretty impressive. I'm just telling
you, he can get it done.
>> Thanks for being here, Richard. Sir,
welcome.
>> Hello. Uh, my name is Chris Keatley.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> Uh, point of order.
>> Sorry, it's half my identity. [laughter]
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Uh, my name's Chris Keatley. Uh, I run
Tuck.
>> I'm sorry, Chris. I
>> Oh, sorry. My name's Chris Keatley. Uh,
I run Tuckley Ranch and Dairy. Um, I'm
one of the farmers that sell at the Life
Fresh Farm stand. Um, I say Tommy has
had an outsiz impact for her little
farmland. For me, this is actually my
second year farming and a lot of what
I'm able to do is because of Tommy. Um,
I live out almost by Eggbert, you know,
where for me it's about a 45 hour minute
drive away from town and turns out
there's not that many people out there
that want to buy chicken. you know,
where being able to get my my product
into the center of town has been a very
very critical part for me for my
infrastructure has allowed me to go down
this endeavor inde
[laughter]
um where
where you were talking about the ability
to keep your land um in what it's
currently doing. I can say that's what I
can very much speak to on it. where
doing the regenerative agriculture,
having the flexibility to be able to
adapt those things is a very critical
piece because a lot of the farming that
me and her do is a lot more of managing
an ecosystem which takes different tools
at different times. Um, for a good
example, I started being able to get all
of the uh scraps from sprouts where I'm
able to feed that in. I had to bring in
more pigs to my farm where I needed more
omnivores to be able to eat that. I
didn't have pigs. I didn't have any
interest in doing pigs before, but to be
able to take advantage of this resource
that I now have, I needed to be able to
pivot in a different way. Um, when I got
into doing this, I also decided to cut
my goats, you know, because for me, it
wasn't as profitable to be able to do it
where when you're adapting and managing
an ecosystem, it's not always going to
be the tools that you were using
yesterday. So I could see that being a
very large restrictive part to this that
that they that taking that away and
making where if she had to build curbs
or things like that I haven't done the
math that's a lot of heads of lettuce to
sell to be able to afferve court you
know where farming is
she spends her life and energy into
building soil like that's for for a
developer that may just be top soil to
remove. But I couldn't tell you how many
times she's looked at soil with a
microscope, you know, to tell you what's
going on in those organisms. And she's
been working on building that for years
and focusing on trying to make a healthy
part to provide nutrient-dense food to
the center of Wyoming. I think if
there's a way to capitalize and build on
that, I think there's a lot of push in
our times for people that are wanting to
get away from Tyson and Smithfield and
things like that. And I feel like she
has the the core opportunity to be able
to do that for our town.
>> Chris, can you remind me? You said you
you grow pigs or raise pigs. What other
things do you do?
>> Uh so I sell I have about 500 egg layers
I sell there. I process myself about a
thousand meat birds. Um that like I sell
chicken wing size, best breast legs,
drumsticks at the farm stand.
>> Sure.
>> Um I have the pork that gets USDA
processed and gets sold there. Um
Milk.
>> Milk. Oh, yeah. [laughter] My cows are
dried up currently, so uh
>> had to help him out with what he sells.
I don't know. [laughter] I I mix a busy
life.
>> Yep, it does. Well, thank you. And it's
one
>> the turkeys. Yep. Yep. But but that's
where mine I'm trying to be able to do
that multiecies farm. And it it takes a
lot of manipulating with what you have,
what people want, what what does well on
your land. You know, the turkeys will
eat more grass than the chickens will.
If she builds the grass, she could do
the cir. You may not have turkeys now,
but they could be a useful tool in the
future.
>> Yeah. So, Chris, just to, you know,
answer I think the question you had
about the curbs and gutters and
sidewalks, you know, um again, as I
stated earlier, you know, we changed our
rules, so that's not a requirement. Now,
if these folks decide they want to build
an apartment building on there, that
changes everything, right? Because
you're changing the use of it, but but
they're not they're not doing that.
They're they're going to be a farm. And
as far as far as as long as they are a
farm, you know, we should not have I
told David, I think when we talked
earlier today, if you uh if if you're
going to uh uh maybe have a big grain
elevator or something on there with a
lot of trucks coming out, we might have
to do something, you know, on the roads,
but they're they're going to run a farm,
they're going to run chickens, they're
going to have they're going to raise
crops and things like that. It should
not trigger the things that you just
asked about. And and we're going to
we're going to try really hard to try to
find a definition of an urban farm. So
that it gives them the flexibility so
that they can as you said you know you
had pigs but now you do something else
because that's what the market said is
the right thing to do. So we're going to
try to find definitions that will allow
that to to be a reality.
>> Absolutely.
>> Yeah. Well for me if there was a way to
work mutually and beneficially because
even like that waste water for a farm I
know where I live I get 14 inches of
rainfall a year. if I had a neighborhood
pump rainfall flowing in, but if there
was a way to get it in that we had a
filtration system for, I feel like
there's ways that a urban farm could be
very beneficial and work and symbiotic
wi with it. And you know, I I think
finding ways to work together with it to
come to beneficial solutions.
>> You know, I told Tommy when we talked on
the phone that uh you know, I think this
is one of those quality of life things
that that people want when you live in a
community. Um, it's it's having, you
know, some shopping opportunities and
some shopping options for healthy food
and it's also great for people like
yourself, other small business people
that can come to their farm stand and
sell. So, we've talked about, you know,
how important that is to our community.
So, I think there's a recognition of it.
I appreciate what you do. Thank you.
Don't forget your hat.
>> Absolutely.
>> Sir, welcome.
>> My name is Gabriel Pac. I am a fifth
generation Cheyenne resident and also a
small business owner. Um, with the farm
stand, my own testimonial is when my
wife and I had a small dog breeding
program. [snorts] We focused more highly
on quality of the canine's lives over
quantity. And Tommy and David were kind
enough to let us bring the dogs out
there and be exposed to animals, be
exposed to multiple people just to
socialize the puppies in that critical 3
to 8 week window um to set them up for a
better life. So many of the benefits
that we see around the farm stand are
not strictly food related but more to
the broader impact that they said Tommy
has a larger a disproportionate impact
positive impact on the community. I've
spoken at length with both Chris and
Tommy about soil biology because that is
and regenerative agriculture that's
another passion of mine. Um, if you ever
read Terry Patchet's book, The Light
Fantastic, the world is coming to an end
and the crowds have taken to the streets
and half of them are have gathered
around the the leaders of the city
demanding that they get their metalsome
hands out of things and they stop
messing everything up and the other half
demands that they find a way to turn
this thing around and fix the problem.
Damn it. [snorts] Heavy is the head that
wears the crown. And no matter what the
city council chooses, 50% of the
population will be angry. And even on a
vote of five to four, we know that all
nine of them are responsible and are to
be held accountable and we're angry.
Damn it. I do think, however, that um to
build on both pre the both the gentlemen
that spoke previously that the
possibility for
pioneering new territory in what does it
look like for urban agriculture,
integrated urban agriculture? What does
this mean for our city? And how can
other cities look to us as an example in
the ways that we have led?
Most of the carbon emissions that come
from agriculture come from food miles.
Food that has to be transported miles
and miles from the grower to the
processor, then back to the processor to
the distributor, from the distributor to
the supermarket, from the supermarket to
the consumer.
I think that by reducing food miles,
we're looking at things for much less
carbon emissions and much better in
terms of climate change or taking care
of our climates, being stewards of the
land that we have. Soil agriculture and
regenerative agriculture. What is the
health of our soil? Ask Chris, we'll be
here all night. However, that is a very
deep rabbit hole and one that has been
sadly neglected in our country on a mass
agricultural scale for close to a
century now. We have now reached a point
where people are asking questions about
where their food comes from. What is the
quality of the soil and the food? What
how can we as a city move forward
blazing a trail for other cities to
follow in our footsteps? I remember a
few years ago when chickens suddenly
became legal in Cheyenne. For that, I
salute the city council. You guys did
wonderful. That was perhaps one of the
best things I have ever heard of our
town. But needless to say, I am proud
and I thank you guys for everything you
do. I ask that we could continue to look
forward to see how we can open new
conversations to increase the quality of
life for all of us and to set a better
example for other towns in our nation.
Thank you,
>> Gabriel. Thanks for being here.
You're looking sharp, young man.
>> Thank you, mayor. Hang on. Give me one
moment. All right. Well, good evening,
Mayor and Council. Um,
>> your name?
>> My name? Oh, yes. My name is Mr.
Matthews. I'm here as a [clears throat]
local resident and business owner. See,
it's closer. And I have uh I have
appreciated the discussion of economic
growth and protecting our small
businesses here in Cheyenne. observing
land. Um, but with that in mind, let's
see, so I don't forget my reference.
Let's see. I'm here regarding the uh
proposed amendments. Let's see, what is
this? To the unified development code
related to uh homebased businesses.
Um,
>> that's a different item. That's not what
we're talking about. Now, this is a uh a
public hearing for the uh annexation of
some pieces of uh of property 100%
surrounded by the city.
>> Yes. Okay. No, no room to add anything.
>> We'll have we'll have time for that
later.
>> Okay.
>> Just not not not our opportunity yet.
>> Are you talking about the ADUs?
>> Sorry. Auxiliary dwelling units. Is that
what you're here to talk about?
>> Uh more of like homebased businesses
registered as a residency and just kind
of what to expect in certain areas.
Yep.
>> If I can get to that later, then that's
fine.
>> We'd be I'm not I'm not sure. We can
sure do that under other business at the
end of the meeting if you'd like.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you. Appreciate you being here
this evening.
>> Nice to see you, too, sir.
>> Well, thank you, sir. Uh, good evening,
Mr. Mayor and members of the council.
It's a lot more nerve-wracking to be on
this side than sitting in those chairs
as I did when I was on the DDA.
>> Um,
identify yourself for the record. My
name is Landon Medina. I'm a local
resident here in Cheyenne. My wife and I
are business owners. Um, and I have had
the pleasure of meeting Tommy and David
recently.
Um, couple things as I was going
through. I was able to also talk with
people um, from the county and in Mr.
Edgar's department um, about where you
guys are on your side of the issue. Um,
and I was able to kind of see points
from both sides. Um, couple questions I
got for you. Uh, regarding the oneyear
mark, if they stop doing a certain task
for a year and then they won't be able
to restart doing it, is there any
parameters laid for like a if a death in
the family happened or something
substantial came up to where they had to
put this on pause for a year, uh, how
they would get it going again? Is there
any anything thought of on that yet?
>> Yeah, I don't think that the state law
contemplates that.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, and L, it might be just so
simple as just bring one chicken, put it
on the property and say, "Okay, we had a
chicken here. We've had a our
agricultural use and you move on." Oh,
>> Charles, you want to Okay,
>> mayor, members of council, Charles
Bloom, planning and development
director. I just want to note that the
way this is being annexed is being zoned
AG, so it would be appropriated use. So
in that scenario, it would be allowed to
continue regardless of the time period
it ceased. They just have to reestablish
it. Um in those cases, they'd have to
either just revive the current use,
which is what it was. If they wish to
expand, they'd have a site plan just
modifying their proposal. So long story
short, they could take as much time off
as they want under the way this is
proposed.
>> Well, that's even better news.
>> Thank you, Charles. You might have to
stay close by for my next question here.
Um, and then you know when Tommy said
that she has big dreams for this farm
stand, I have I've talked to some of you
guys on city council and before you guys
got on city council, you had big dreams
as well, right? Um, I just want to know
if what the rules and regulations are
for if they decide to expand into maybe
just another animal or put up more green
houses. Um, I just haven't clearly got
an answer on that and I was wondering
what you guys had.
>> Charles, did you want to answer that?
I told you.
>> Does your AG answer comply here too?
>> Mayor, members of of council, I was
waiting for the look to come up and
answer that question. Um, regarding
expansion, every use typically has a
site plan that's documented or
inventoried. When a new use is annexed
in the town, we have them fill out the
voluntary land use documentation form
where they can draw rectangles, a simple
and aerial map saying, "This is where
chickens are. This is where I grow
products. This is the area I use to move
my hen houses around." And that's the
the land use. Um, in the event that they
wish to expand it to another portion of
the lot or a larger area on the land, we
would ask for the simple site plan,
which does have $100 review fee. And
that simple site plan would simply say
this is where we're going to expand to.
It is agriculture. Um, agriculture is a
unique use in the city. We we support
it. We support urban agriculture and
urban farming operations. I mean that
agriculture does not have any
requirements for landscaping buffer
yards to be installed. It it really has
very limited um items that would be
reviewed. Things that would be reviewed
that would also be reviewed in the
county today are if you put a farm stand
in or expanded that you'd be expected to
pave your ADA parking space. That's
requirement city or county. Um, you'd
also have to um make sure that you are,
you know, building to applicable codes
for items that are are buildings that
are public buildings.
But in this case, when it comes to
adding on to the farm area, it could be
as simple as just identifying where that
new farm area is on the map and then we
look at what is the scale. Um,
ultimately, if it's just a small
addition, say 5% of the site, that's not
going to trigger anything. uh we are
required um to look at is there
proportionality. If they are putting a
small dollar amount into this
investment, it is not reasonable or
practical to require tens of thousands
or even hundreds of thousand dollars
worth of improvements. Those
improvements only occur when we have
major improvements to a site. You see it
all around town. Um, we've had a lot of
pro properties where they have turned
over from a vacant building and you
might see a new storefront in there.
They almost look about the same. Um,
that's because we're we're doing these
small change of use site plans which
don't really trigger much of anything.
But if they were to modify this farm to
put in a 30,000 foot farm stand, maybe
triple the land that they would be
farming, maybe put in large structures
that had indoor vertical farming, those
types of items, that's a significant
investment and that would trigger a
conversation where whether you're in the
city or the county, a lot of these
conversations would have occurred
anyway.
>> Mr. Medina, did that answer your
question?
>> That that does.
>> Uh Mr. Mayor, could when Mr. Bloom's
really quick leaving that podium, um
could could we ask him a few questions
or would you would you rather wait until
we
>> Mr. Medina, why don't you finish and
then we'll
>> Okay,
>> during the public hearing, we'll have
time for the council if you don't mind.
Write your question down so you don't
forget
>> to you, Mr. Mayor. Um
guys, just my two cents on this. I uh
I'm just a normal guy. Um, so my two
cents might not mean much, but I'd like
to think that I got my kind of I'd like
to think that I'd know kind of what
people of our community are thinking and
feeling. And uh, on this topic, I would
suggest that you guys postpone this
until all the information is clearly out
and all these questions are answered.
Once again, just my two cents on that.
Thank you guys.
Miss Woodhouse, I haven't seen you at
this podium for a very long time.
>> It's been a few years.
Gay Woodhouse, 1912 Capitol Avenue,
fifth floor. Uh, I came here as
basically a friend of the Nisley's and
their wife Ranch. Uh, possibly an
attorney later. We'll see how things go.
But my primary goal was to see if we
would postpone this matter. Uh I do
believe there's still a lot of questions
that need to be resolved. You know, we I
couldn't not talk because we used to
fight about annexation almost every day
when it was the three of us or four of
us. But
>> she has a really really cool bike and I
think we paid for it with all the times
we had to battle back and forth.
[laughter] So
>> that's true. That's true. Yeah. But
anyway, I I really would appreciate it
if it could be postponed. so that some
of these things could be worked out. You
know, it wasn't the Nisley's fault that
the city grew up around them. You know,
they have a nice 8 acre area. It's
beautiful. It can be developed further
in terms of agriculture. Uh they have
dreams, you know, and their dreams
didn't just go away because they put a
motel in or a housing development or
whatever, you know, it doesn't go away.
And I think that when people have dreams
that we as individuals ourselves need to
respect that and to give them, you know,
the time and the asurances they have so
they don't need to lie awake at night
worrying about what's going to happen.
And I do like the idea of an actual
urban an urban
land urban agricultural
uh ordinance that would really specify
all the things that can be done and the
improvements that could be made. And it
happens in other cities in Colorado.
They have them. I don't think it would
be that hard to find something that
could be modeled after and make sure
that they are doing what they need to do
and what they plan to do and aren't just
hamstrung because they surrounded by
city property and they can be annexed
you know and I do also want to say I
really appreciate you know some of the
requirements back in the day when we
used to fight all the time you know
we're not having to do curb and gutter
we're not having to hook up to uh city
sewer and water right away and that
Those kinds of things make a huge
difference. But this is a kind of a
unique property. Very unique property.
And so is number seven, the one that the
lady talked about with her um uh
>> her barn and her
>> her barn. Yeah. Right. Barnois. Yeah.
>> So I I think it might be an opportunity
for us to really make some good headway
on something, but maybe just give us a
slow roll. Give us give us some more
time.
>> Thank you. Nice to have you here
tonight.
>> Thank you,
>> ma'am.
>> Hello. Um, my name is Kelsey French. I
actually am one of the farmer's
daughters. Um, I help out at WFresh. I
grew up here 28 years. I moved back
recently. Um, and I I just kind of want
to say like the astonishment of how much
we've grown here in Cheyenne and it just
keeps going out east and west. And I
mean, we pride ourselves on being the
Cowboy State, but it seems like the
Cowboys state wants nothing to do with
the Cowboys. They want to push us out.
Um I I don't think that any of us feel
that you guys are going to put us out of
business. I mean, I've watched my mom
grow. It's great. She owns Spotted Dair
Farm. Um the amount of milk that we
bring in is right around 300 jars a
week, if that. I mean, the the city
itself is proud of it. Um, I I think the
growing concern is the prices of things.
You annex and they're going to have to
get a building permit. Um, I actually
recently seen a um release of the
questions that were asked and the tax
was actually $23 instead of the $90.
>> Actually, it was we figured out when we
talked to the assessor, it's actually
$90.
>> Okay. So, that must be old.
>> We had we had a calculator, but it
calculated a little high. Okay.
But I I don't know. I just I I'm asking
to postpone it. I've seen it grow there.
It's We're not a skyscraper city. I
mean, that's not what we are. We're the
Great Plains. We ride horses. We have
animals. Those kids in the apartments
probably look over at the Nisle's Place
and they see those animals. Geez, I wish
I could do that. I grew up with friends
who would actually bring more animals
into their property so that kids in town
would get the experience to show it the
Laramie County Fair and be able to take
it to Douglas. And I I I just asked for
it to be postponed. I mean, it it's a
small little farm. I don't see it
hurting anything. It was there before
all those big apartment complexes and
those huge hotels went up.
>> Kelsey, thanks for being here. Keep
milking those cows.
>> It's a lot of work. I know. Seven days a
week, morning and night, right? [snorts]
>> Sir, welcome.
>> Good evening. Uh my name is Wade Blunt
and uh I been listening to uh all the
comments uh in favor of the Niclley's
and I I too echo that that sentiment. Um
but I would just uh kindly ask the the
the mayor, Mr. mayor and the council.
Uh, I know um several of of you uh have
owned businesses in Cheyenne or may
still currently own businesses and I
would just um humbly ask that you you
you this this uh council would consider
putting yourself in the nicely shoes and
uh what what if it was your business
that was facing what the nicely and and
if you if you could um for just a moment
take your political hats off and and and
put those small business hats on and and
again put yourself in uh their shoes and
um just would humbly ask that you would
you know we we have so many we have data
centers and so many businesses that have
have come to Cheyenne and I would just
implore the council to Treat
these folks just like any other big
corporation that comes with the respect
that you would for like again a data
center or any other business that has
come to Cheyenne in in over the last
several years. And uh just uh again just
echo what everybody else has said just
uh ask that you would kindly consider
and postponing this until all the
questions can be fairly asked. Thank you
and wait I will just share with you I
have had a small business for a lot of
years in Larmy County and I have talked
to the nicely and tried to understand uh
what's going on and I'm working hard to
try to come up with definitions and
things to help them be successful. Um so
it's not like we're we're not having
those conversations sir. We're not doing
exactly what you've asked and we'll do
our very best to try to make this the
best situation that we can. Ma'am,
>> welcome.
>> Okay. Hopefully I'm very tall, so
[laughter]
>> hopefully you all can hear me. Good
evening. Good evening, everybody. Um,
sorry this is a little nerve-wracking
for me.
>> You're doing fine. Take a deep breath.
We'll be good.
>> But I felt it was very important to get
up here because
>> you got to tell us your name first.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. My name is Haley Arthur.
I am a Cheyenne resident. I live only
but a couple minutes away from the farm
stand. Um, and thank you for having me.
So, I wanted to just address my thoughts
and concerns here. My family and I are
huge on community supporting the
community, supporting local businesses.
We love Cheyenne. We love all the small
businesses here in town. And I came
across recently the farm stand and I
have enjoyed attending and coming and
supporting them. Um, my family and I
love being self-suffi self
self-sufficient and homesteading and um,
eating cleaner and having the farm stand
nearby close by is so important and I
think that many of the community members
would agree to that. um the importance
of having the options to organic
holistic foods and knowing where it
comes from and again having their option
in town is just so nice and convenience
and I love that and being able to
support not only the farm stand but
everybody that they bring in, all the
businesses that they bring in and I just
think that is so important for building
our communities and being um closer
together. I just I think that's so
important and My my thoughts are is to
postpone this annexation until they can
get all of their answers um and come to
the right resolution. Um I just I think
that's really really important for them
is just to uh postpone.
>> So all the young kids here, they know
they eat their vegetables, they'll grow
tall like you, right?
>> Yeah, exactly. [laughter]
>> Haley, thanks for being here.
>> Thank you.
>> Oh, sorry, Jeff. Yes, ma'am. Welcome.
>> Good evening, Mr. Mayor and council
members. My name is Julia Lens and I'm
>> Say that again.
>> My name is Julia Lens.
Y u L I A. Last name L N Z. I get that a
lot [laughter] in case that helps.
>> It helped a lot. Thank you.
>> Sure. And I'm a resident of the
Southside.
And I think I could stand here tonight
and talk about all of the amazing things
that the farm stand does. Um and I know
you guys are totally on board for what
they're already doing. And that's not
the issue. The issue is, and Mr. Mr.
Mayor, I've heard you say this a couple
times is working on the definition of an
urban farm. Right. And that's really
what I'm asking for this evening. Can we
please postpone in order to find that
definition? Um why is the annexation so
important right now? And that's really
my biggest question because it sounds
like this has been in the works for 3
years or so. um why can we not have
maybe a week or two to understand what
an urban farm means and not just to
support the one that we're so lucky to
have but what if we can make more and
what if we can be an example for other
cities
um that's a really great opportunity for
us
>> and you I think you brought up a point
that maybe the audience doesn't
understand what our process is so
tonight we're going to have a public
hearing and then it's going to go to the
uh public services committee then it'll
come back here in two weeks. Then it'll
go back to the public service committee
and then come back here. So we'll have
another four um opportunities for a
public meeting uh where we can work on
all those issues. Uh and I think if I
remember right, March 9th is probably
the date that this would so we have a
month from today that we can start
working on these definitions and uh and
try to come up with those answers um as
as we go through that. So this is a
great opportunity to listen and
understand what the questions are and
then we can start to endeavor to answer
those questions.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I wasn't aware of
that. Appreciate it.
>> Thank you so much for being here.
Support local.
You guys are all wearing green. I just
love this. David, nice job.
>> It's the only green shirt I own.
>> Tommy, nice job.
>> Um, my name is Michelle Michael. I am a
farmer. I'm with Spotted Dair Farms. And
um I [clears throat] hadn't planned on
speaking today, but I do want to say
that if it wasn't for WFresh, I would
not probably still be in business. Um I
don't know if
people are aware of how much work it is
to milk animals, milk cows. I have dairy
goats. Um a lot of times I do this by
myself
and [snorts] so [clears throat] it is
very important to me. Um, the nicely are
wonderful people. It's very important to
me that this farm stand continues and I
do ask that you postpone the annexation
so that they can get their questions
answered. Um, I have questions. I asked
them, they can't answer. So, be very
much appreciated.
Thank you,
>> Michelle. I have a great uncle that was
a dairy farmer. So, I I have a little
bit of a idea. As a young man, it is a
lot of work. Seven days a week
>> it is. Yeah. No time off.
>> You never you you can never not wait.
>> That's right.
>> Thank you. Hello.
>> Thank you.
>> Welcome.
>> Hi. Um I didn't get the green memo, but
I am here for um
>> I'm not sure you can talk then.
[laughter]
>> Welcome. Um, I am, my name is Leon Jetum
and I'm a resident of Cheyenne and um, I
use beef tallow on my face and I love
it. Um, and I've always had to order it
online and then I finally found a local
beef towel producer that makes products
for um, my consumption that I can use
and they get their tallow uh, from
Wofresh. And so I just thought it would
be great. Um, I know you guys have uh
kind of
um, what am I saying? You guys have kind
of answered some questions tonight that
have been concerning for them. Um, but I
know that there's still more and I know
that all they're asking for is a little
time. And so I just wanted to bring
awareness to um, the council that they
aren't just a piece of land. They have a
blanket web over the whole community
that they spread to. So,
>> thanks for being here. Appreciate it.
Green. Next time.
>> Hi.
>> Good evening. My name
>> You got the memo, so you're good.
>> Yes, I did. My name is Michelle Johnson
Bowen. I'm a recent transplant
affiliated with the military, of course.
Um, I am also a town planner. Um, I
worked for a city in Arizona for 20
years. And I will say I appreciate the
work that I believe his name was Connor.
um explained about the annexation,
legal non-conforming use and rolling
over into an agricultural zoning. Um I
would have done the same thing to try to
make it as
seamless as possible, although I
understand there will always be issues
of fees, issues of new requirements. Um
and that's scary. I've seen it as a town
planner and I had it happen to me as
well. So I I appreciate those fears. Um
my question is with a response of three
parties out of 14 parcels for the
annexation as a whole. I'm wondering if
that is about a typical proportion of
responses. Again, being on the town
planner side, we do something, nobody
responds, they figure it out two years
later, and it's for our heads and your
heads.
So, that's that's one of my concerns in
general. I will say as a recent
transplant,
um what's today, the 9th, I have been
here less than 30 days. I did go to the
farm store because I I found it before I
realized there was this whole thing
going on. um just as a healthy eating
initiative for myself and my family. And
as far as answering questions, I'm
assuming Director Bloom knows this, but
the American Planning Association has an
entire food systems division that can
absolutely help you with these
definitions.
>> We've been looking at those today.
>> Excellent. Y
>> very good.
>> So,
>> so did you guys move here with an active
duty member?
>> Um my husband's a military contractor.
>> Okay. So,
>> very good.
>> Now that all of our kids are gone, I can
travel with him.
>> Nice. Welcome.
>> Thank you.
>> Are you going to be here for a while? Do
we need to get a resume to you for
planning or what do we need to do?
>> No, we will only be here. We will only
be here about four to five months.
>> All right. Give us a shot. Thank you.
>> Thank [laughter] you.
>> Welcome. Thank you,
>> sir. Did you want to speak?
>> Did you want to speak? Anybody else?
Welcome,
>> Mr. Mayor. Uh, council members, good
evening. My name is, uh, Steven Love.
I'm a longtime resident of Cheyenne,
Wyoming. Um, I was born [clears throat]
just down the road at the hospital. Um,
for
most of my life, uh, the first 16 years,
I lived in the county, um, about 30
minutes from Cheyenne. And um much like
this property, I was uh transplanted
into the city. Um so I think I can
provide maybe a unique perspective in
that manner. Um
a lot of the issues um that the these
folks have brought up is um you know
what what does the future look like? And
um I I would just ask the council to
maybe look at a new framework. Maybe um
maybe a the current definition um isn't
expansive enough. Um a lot of people
have brought up, oh, you need to have
one chicken and I think the state law
maybe doesn't protect them well enough
um in this process. So perhaps the
council could look at um maybe a new
framework and
um how that would help bring the um farm
into maybe a little more willingly into
the city. Um
thank you
>> Stephen. You know, it's you make brought
up a good point about chickens and I I
learned from talking to Tommy that she
has 120 some chickens right now and if
you don't have a couple roosters, they
get out of hand. So, we don't allow
roosters in the city limits, but because
it's an urban farm and it was a legal
use before the uh um inexation would
happen that they'll be able to keep the
roosters. So I do think that there is
some some understanding of that and um
and making sure that we we give them
what they need.
>> I I think more than that what I mean is
um if they have um you know one one cow
can they have two next year you know and
what does that mean? Um do they have to
you know file a document with the city
to have another cow or even to build a
fence? Um living in the county we I
lived on a small ranch. I've built more
fence than I care to admit. And
>> that's why you're a city boy now. I
understand. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Um Yes, sir. And um you know, do every
time they have to put a post in the
ground. I I know that's an extreme
example, but I I think you understand my
point is that you know, where do we draw
the line? Um and and where do they get
into that
>> point where they have to start putting
in curb and gutter? Um, and I I think to
that point too, um, I was formerly
employed employed by Aztec Construction.
Um, I installed utilities. Um, and I was
on the Dell Range project um, this last
I'm sorry, uh, two years ago, I believe
it was. Um, putting in that large storm
sewer. And there was several county
pockets through there that you guys
annexed
um while we were putting that road in um
or you were in the process of annexing.
And um I think maybe
two of the four properties along Del
Range um got utilities put in um with
that road project. Um,
I think perhaps you guys could look at
um, you know, the total of what you're
looking to do in the future. Um, because
some of those properties did not get
those utilities um, up to their property
line. Um so when they do want to or are
forced to
um tie into the city services,
they will they will have to front that
cost and they'll have to tear up Dell
Range. Um that beautiful new road that
we built.
>> Not what we want. Thank you.
>> Y appreciate you being here tonight,
sir. Jennifer, do you have any online?
>> Let's take the first one.
>> Miss Allen, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you. Hi, can you guys hear me?
>> Miss Allen, we hear you just loud and
clear.
>> Hi, Susan Allen, a resident of Cheyenne.
Thank you so much for letting me um
speak. I am just here to strongly uh
agree with those have who have spoken
before me to postpone the decision on
annexing Yfresh.
Um, I just want to remind this governing
body and I'm sure you guys are aware
that Cheyenne has a proud horiculture
and agricultural roots dating back to
1928 when Congress directed the USDA to
establish the Cheyenne horicultural
field station west of town on city lease
land. It tested thousands of plants in
our semierid climate, releasing hearty
varieties like the Ogalala strawberry
and also Cheyenne mums um which is
Cheyenne's official flower dating back
uh to 1970.
Um there were a couple of senators that
fought really hard to establish this
station here in Cheyenne. There was only
three, one in Mandan, North Dakota, one
in Oklahoma, and one here in Cheyenne.
and its work was primarily to see how we
could survive in this aid climate and
grow fruits and vegetables in the
absence of a nearby grocery store. Um
the work helped make um the high plains
more livable um through local food
production and shelter belts. Um why
fresh farm continues that legacy today.
For over um 15 years, the family farm
has supplied fresh chemical-free
produce, greens, eggs, milk, and more to
hundreds of families in and around
Cheyenne. It reduces food miles,
preserves green space, and supports
sustainable local agricultural
um local agriculture. Um I speak from
experience. Um I used to own and operate
a small farm in Windsor, Colorado. Um we
were required to use city of Gley water
and the cost became so prohibitive um it
forced us to uh stop farming. Small
urban farms run on very very thin
margins. Um additional expenses from any
kind of additional regulations,
utilities or taxes can easily make or
break the difference between succeeding
and failing. I realize while there may
not be some upfront costs right now, I
feel like that that creep could um
affect their farm um substantially.
And so I too would like to um echo some
of the other comments about creating um
we have such an opportunity with our
rich history in agriculture and
horiculture here in Cheyenne to lead the
way. Cheyenne's special. We are special
people here in Cheyenne and I think we
can do a good job. Um, you know, we
require a lot of parks to be built when
new businesses come around. Why are we
not building um, you know, and those are
just grass that takes up more water with
no no benefit other than to be able to
play on them? But what if we established
urban green spaces that maybe had a
horicultural easement on them that would
be protected in perpetuity?
>> Thank you so much. Thank you.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
Did you want to speak?
>> Good evening. Welcome.
>> Hello. I've never done this before, so
excuse me.
>> Hey, you're going to be just fine. Just
tell us your name and just what you
>> My name is Kim Stevens.
>> Kim, welcome.
>> Thank you. I love the Wild Farm stand. I
haven't been there very often, but I
think it's a great contribution to our
city. And my question is,
it's been there for so long. What would
be the advantage of annexing that piece
of property? I don't understand that.
>> You know, that's probably the first
person tonight that's asked that
question. Maybe I can go back in a
little bit of the history for you. um in
2022 at our goal setting session, you
know, I got elected to the city council
in uh the year 2000 and uh our our um
you know, it's maybe my vision of that
would be that at that time was that
county pockets will eventually be
assimilated into the city. you know, mom
and dad dies, the kids live in Arizona,
it'll get annexed when somebody buys it
and wants to bring it up and develop it,
you know, and we just took a long-term
approach to that. But we started to have
a few uh jurisdictional challenges that
came with law enforcement and with uh uh
mostly with the fire department where
911 would be called and we had a
confusion of who was supposed to be
there and I think our governing body
looked at that and said, you know, um we
probably just need to clean that up. Um
and we had a hundred How many do we
have, Charles? county pockets 160.
It was a lot. And uh and so we had a we
had a few situations that were just
really uncomfortable for all of us. And
the state law uh says that if a property
is 100% surrounded by the city, uh the
city council can um can just bring them
into the city limits and clean that up.
And we spent a lot of time, as I said
earlier, to make sure that we we could
reduce the impact to the land owner as
much as we can. But that's where the
genesis came from was to see um you know
these jurisdictional challenges and we
were worried that you know while we
didn't ever have a less of life in one
of those we were worried that that might
happen. Somebody had a heart attack or
there was a fire and we we screwed up
the response you know could there be a a
damage to someone that would be
terrible. And so we just decided in 20
uh 22 to make that a county goal. And so
we've been working on this ever since.
We've done nine. We just finished or we
will finish tonight, I believe, the
ninth u of our um annexations u of of
all the county pockets. This is the last
grouping of them. And u and then all the
county pockets in Shine will be annexed
and we'll we'll have eliminated that
jurisdictional challenge. So to answer
your question, that's why we're doing
this. Um it's not to punish anybody or
do anything like that. We don't make any
more money because of this. It was
mostly just because of those
jurisdictional challenges. if that helps
you
>> somewhat. So much. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Go ahead and finish if you had
some more things to say.
>> No, I just it's just pure and simple. I
love Wyom Farm and I think we should
have sustainable [snorts] homegrown food
instead of the
stuff that we eat out of out of the
shopping centers. You know,
>> I hear David makes a good cup of coffee,
too. So, I'm going to go check that out.
>> They make good everything.
>> Good. Thank you, D.
>> Thank you so much.
Jennifer, who do you have?
>> Tatiana M, you can unmute yourself.
>> Hi, can you hear me? Okay,
>> we can hear you, Tatiana. You introduce
yourself, please.
>> Yes, this is Tatiana Misenova. I am
actually located in Colorado.
Um, and I just wanted to of course echo
everything everyone is saying about um,
David and Tommy and um, everything
they're doing for the community. I know
I don't live in Cheyenne, but I drive up
there and it's such a joy to visit the
farm and visit the farm stand, get to
know the farmers. It is so inspiring.
And I did grow up um, in a family where
we grew our all our own fruits and
vegetables. We had chickens and pigs and
um so in a way being there at the farm
stand and talking to all the farmers and
having access to fresh local produce and
um meats and milk has really like
reignited that passion in me and I every
time I'm there I learned so much just
from talking to them and hopefully
someday I'll be able to have a farm of
my own but um when people have spoken
earlier about like maybe you know this
can help be an example or you know lead
other cities to do the same thing. I
absolutely want to say that definitely
would [clears throat] inspire me. it
already has and I sure hope that
Cheyenne can um you know postpone this
and nexting and figure out a way for
wife to still be there and to support
all the local farmers that are able to
sell there. I know Michelle I have
access to her milk through White Fresh
and I love it so much. I have lactose
intolerance, but the milk from
Michelle's and you know the raw milk,
goat milk, I'm able to have that. So for
me, an hour drive to Cheyenne to get
access to that is such a blessing. I'm
like, I will take it. I can have milk
thanks to them, you know. So, I think it
could be even helpful for folks who
might have other allergies and could
learn a thing or two about, you know,
what they can do to be able to have
access to food um from WFresh that they
might otherwise not be able to due to
the processing of the food, you know,
elsewhere.
So, thank you so much,
>> Tatiana. I learned something today. I
did not realize that lactose intolerance
intolerances were for dairy cows, but
goat goat milk is not have doesn't have
that. So, thanks for the lesson. I
learned something new today.
>> You're welcome. Thank you,
>> Jennifer.
>> Bartmus Smith, you can go ahead and
unmute yourself.
>> Uh, yes. Can you hear me?
>> We can, Mr. Smith. Welcome.
>> Um, actually, actually, uh, that's just
my email address. Uh, my name is Charles
Miller. Um, and I just wanted to say uh
I have been listening to the testimony
uh tonight and it was the Wresh family's
words that had impacted me the most. You
could hear clearly that they do not want
to be annexed and that they are afraid
of being pushed into something your own
staff cannot fully explain yet. U Mr.
Mayor, if I could ask you a question
possibly.
>> I'm here.
>> Um do you know how many distinct land
owners are in this annexation map?
Was it 16? I believe it was 16, sir.
>> Okay. And do you know the percentage of
the owners that are for the annexation
versus the ones that are not?
>> I think we've t heard from three. Two
were either in favor or agnostic. And at
our public meeting, we heard one. I
think we had a second one here this
evening that uh um has a barn and horses
that's pretty comfortable the way things
are.
>> I see. Well, I did hear some, and this
is kind of off my script here, but I did
hear some things about the lack of um
proper notice. Um, you know, and and
personally speaking, I have uh had some
similar issues uh with the county. Um,
but that was a little bit off, but I
just wanted to say uh [clears throat]
with uh with that percentage of owners
or whatever, if if the owners could get
in touch with each other, then it'll be
great. So, um, this is this is to the
owners, okay? And, uh, Wyoming law gives
you a safety valve under under WS15146B
if land owners representing more than
50% of the value or the area of this
territory file written protests within
20 business days after this hearing,
then no further action can be taken on
this annexation area for two years. In
plain language, even if the council
doesn't listen tonight, a majority of
you acting together can legally put this
annexation on ice for two years. That is
not a favor from the city. That is your
a right you already have. And it doesn't
end there. If two years from now, the
city tries again and a majority of you
once again file timely written protests,
you trigger another two-year stop. As
long as you stay organized and keep
hitting that 50% threshold on time, you
can keep saying no and keep stopping new
attempts. So to the Wresh family and
your neighbors, you are not powerless
here. If this process stays as unclear
and risky as you describe, you have a
lawful way to say no and to keep saying
it while you buy yourselves time. Thank
you,
>> Charles. I I would tell you, sir, that
you need to keep reading, okay? Because
if you read 15146C,
it says that if the city initiates um an
annexation and it's 75% of the uh
surrounded, the landowner exemption does
not apply. In this case, every one of
these properties is 100% surrounded. And
so all of that great um um
research that you did uh is exempt from
from the lens. So just read the next the
next piece of it and you'll understand
that, sir.
>> Oh, okay. I will go ahead and uh you
know
>> 15146
>> I will keep uh my uh attention on this
particular annexation and and continue
to try to provide support for them.
Thank you.
>> Appreciate you, sir. Thank you. Yes,
ma'am. Welcome.
>> Hello. Uh my name is Aaron Edwards. I'm
with Ward One. I just wanted to make a
point of clarification here. Um, you
mentioned that the looking at the plots
that were within city limits that were
county pockets and there were
jurisdictional issues on response from
first responders. Um, I'm not going to
speak on half of any agency. In my
part-time side gig, I've been a
firefighter in the county for 23 years.
And in my observations, I can tell you
that when we get called to something, we
don't look at a map first to find out if
it's our jurisdiction. We go we go to
help those folks. And if in the course
of that we discover it's a different
jurisdiction, we call dispatch and have
them dispatch that correct jurisdiction
out to come take over the scene. And
Chief Dyorn may have something contrary
in his experience in his many years as
Cheyenne Fire. But I've also witnessed
Cheyenne Fire do the same where uh
they've been called and they call us.
We've been called to Cheyenne areas
again right on that jurisdictional
boundary and then we give them a call
and have them come out to their scene.
So, I just want to clarify that so that
the citizens don't think that emergency
responders are picking and choosing and
looking at maps before we respond. We're
we're here to help the community no
matter what jurisdiction they ser they
sit in.
>> Well, Erin, thanks for being a
firefighter and and I I I appreciate
very much the fact that when we call
911, we don't care what color the truck
is or what the patch is on the sleeve,
right? When you call 911, you just want
somebody to be there. But um you know
the response from inside the city limits
of a Cheyenne Fire Department is much
quicker. Um and so um you know if it's a
we had one just recently where on Ridge
Road where there was a fire and they
called the county and it took a while to
get there. It wasn't terrible uh but we
found out it was in the city limits and
we had a fire station just around the
corner. We could have been there
significantly faster and that's where
somebody was standing at their house.
they saw a fire and they called 911 and
they the the person who made that phone
call was actually in the county and so
when the uh the dispatch looked at that
they said, "Oh, it must be a county
fire." And so they sent the fire
district from the county. Um and and the
response was delayed. Not not by
horrible amount, but had that county
pocket been in the city, the city fire
truck would have been there a minute or
two sooner. And again, that might have
saved a life. And those are the kind of
jurisdictional things that happen. So,
we're not complaining about, you know,
the quality of the fire department.
We're just saying that sometimes those
things get confused and somebody might
get hurt in that situation and this is a
way the governing body could clean that
up.
>> Do you know the address of that
structure fire by chance?
>> Holland Court. Um, it was just south of
Holland Court.
>> So, yeah, the the station that responded
to that was actually pretty quick unless
you've got dispatch logs that prove
otherwise.
>> Yeah, it was.
>> So, it wasn't delayed. It was it was
pretty quick. That's my fire department.
>> Yep. No.
>> So, I can confirm
>> we we we we looked at we looked at that
and and and I say we're not being really
critical of it but you know that was
just it shows you that when somebody
calls from a county pocket dispatch
doesn't know where the fire is. They
just say they see flames right and so
they called a county fire department and
um um you're right the the fire
authority um they're good partners. It's
amazing how much we help each other and
we need to continue to do that.
>> Yeah, we definitely like working with
the city. So
>> Chief Koi does a wonderful job. We talk
regularly. He's a good man. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Who's next? Jennifer.
>> Nobody else. All right. This is the last
call for public comment in the room. Is
anybody else just have a feeling that
they'd just like to share with us?
All right. We're going to close the
public comment section and open up to
the governing body. Mr. Wolf, you had
some questions maybe for staff.
>> I I did, Mr. Mayor. Thank you very much.
And um for Mr. Bloom if if he would
join us.
>> Going to ask you questions, Mr. Wolf.
>> Through you, Mr. Mayor. Thank you. Um
Mr. Bloom, you're familiar with the
city. How many urban farms do we have?
>> Mayor, through you to members of
council.
Urban farms as the one such as Wresh.
This is the only one that I'm aware of.
>> Okay. Do we have a farm extension office
in the city building or the city
departments?
>> Mayor, through you. No, we don't have a
farm extension office.
>> All right. So, to the heart of the
question before us tonight, where do you
think we stand in terms of your
discussions uh with the Nicely about
this annexation?
Uh, and do you think from the department
standpoint that you have addressed all
of their questions or is there more that
you need to spend time talking with them
about?
>> Mayor 32, Council Member Wolf, from the
land use planning standpoint, we do
believe that we have adequately
addressed the land use elements, which
is the definition of the use such as
agriculture and limited agriculture.
However, we do recognize that there is
some uncertainty with the Nicely and
their property. Um, so we are going to
be looking into creating that urban farm
definition to give them more comfort
with the annexation.
>> M Mr. Mayor, uh, follow up on that. I
mean, so how long a process is that, Mr.
Bloom to create a uh a new ordinance uh
regarding uh farming.
>> Not that we need an ordinance and such.
We're just looking for a definition.
>> A definition.
>> Mayor, members of the council, in our
unified development code, there are
provisions for the director to be able
to make interpretations and provide
additional clarification
administratively when there are
uncertainties within the code. If one
visits our unified development code
website, you will see zoning uh
implementation and policy documents at
the bottom that frequently answer some
of the questions we've received over the
years. Some of those have been deleted
as we've made code changes that follow
up with them. Uh one of our current ones
we have that's uh really recognized is
what is our our definition of uh sound
that's not discernable at the property
line and that is in relation to data
centers when they're constructed. What
is a o audible limit that's allowed
nearby? That one's being frequently
used. Uh we have one also for little
free libraries like what is a little
free library? When are they permitted?
Where are they permitted? How can they
be permitted? So we have that on the
website. Um it's only uh it seems
appropriate for us to further clarify
what exactly an urban farm is and how it
falls into this agricultural definition.
And based on the information that we've
received from Mr. Nicely, um, his wife
Tommy, and everyone else at this public
hearing, I do believe and throughout
this whole process, I do believe we have
a strong foundation to be able to walk
something forward to folks at the next,
uh, public services committee this
upcoming Tuesday, uh, which we will be
able to present that and that would be
administrative. with those documents,
their policy, we
we are required to follow that policy,
but eventually we will pull it into the
municipal code. Uh so it would become an
ordinance. Uh so that is when it would
take a little bit longer to go through,
but we want to take it for a test drive
first to make sure it's something that
works for everybody so we don't have to
try to undo it through three readings
and a public hearing and a trip to the
planning commission.
>> Uh thank you. Um M Mr. Mayor, just one
more followup on that if I might.
Um
well, I guess I mean as we as we've
listened to all of this testimony today
now almost two hours worth um and we're
being asked to postpone this and I I I I
am trying to just assess uh for myself
you know actually if we're going to try
and get to
the resolution of these issues is a
postponement really in the best interest
of of the parties, Mr. Mrs. Nicely, or
should we let our processes go forward
for the next really full month now to
actually work through these issues. We
can always at the end of it, I assume,
decide that we didn't want to annex. But
um I um I I think part of that is just
sort of what's your assessment of of
what would be the most helpful thing at
the moment?
>> Mr. Bloom.
>> Mayor 3 to Council Member Wolf. Uh this
is a unique ordinance because it's an
annexation ordinance. With the
annexation ordinance, there's a public
hearing that's required under state
statute that occurs at the beginning of
the process. That's today, right now. If
this were another ordinance like a
zoning, a unified development code text
amendment, a vacation ordinance of a
right of way, all we would have done
today is read it and refer to committee.
And that committee meeting would be the
first time that would have any public
discussion. So with that being the case,
I believe we still have a lot of
additional times when we can have a
conversation on this. We have two
committee meetings and we have
additional two meetings of the full city
council in the governing body that we
can um discuss these items at. And at
all of those meetings, we do have the
ability to postpone if we see that we're
running into a a roadblock or a concern
or something that needs to be addressed
or realigned. So, I'd recommend to
continue to move forward with the
referral.
>> U Mr. Mayor, just one further comment.
Um I I appreciate very much your cander
on that and I appreciate very much Mr.
Bloom and to Connor and your staff
uh how much time you have spent on this.
I mean the the the reality is that the
annexation process of these pockets has
been a singular achievement of Mayor
Collins's uh mayorship and of many
people on this council. with your help
and the help of your staff. Uh and I I
just think we we need to recognize that
and we also need to find the sort of
best path forward. I mean what we have
heard today is a an awful lot of very
compelling testimony and I mean my
wife's a master gardener. I love I love
plants and I love ecosystems. So, um,
struggling with all of that, but, um,
thanks thanks for your answers.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. White,
>> uh, just just a question and it kind of
uh pertains to what Charles was just
talking about. Um, in my time on
council,
we to my in my memory, we've never
postponed
uh or move for a postponement right out
of a public hearing.
>> It's not option. It's not
>> that's that's what I thought.
>> We're just here to listen today.
>> Okay. And so, just for clarification
sake, and for folks who are here, no
postponement will be made tonight, it
will be referred. If you look at item 15
on our agenda, that I this item that
we're we've just been uh talking about
for the last couple of hours, that item
is referred to the public service
committee which will meet on Tuesday.
Usually it's Monday, but because of the
President's Day holiday, it will meet on
Tuesday. And then uh discussion can take
place there and then a motion for
postponement. the committee can
recommend postponement to the governing
body's next meeting at the 24th. Just
wanted to go through that process. Um I
did not think that we could uh postpone
out of a public hearing. It I could
never remember that happening before.
Just wanted to clarify.
>> Yeah, you can't postpone unless you have
a motion to do something and uh we don't
have anything before us today to do
that. Today is just to listen and to
hear people's feedback. Tuesday, we'll
actually have a motion and uh and then
there'll be an opportunity at that time
um for the count the public service
committee to vote no, to postpone or to
vote yes. I think those are the only
three options they have. Jennifer,
>> Dr. Aldridge, you can go ahead.
>> Thank you, Mayor Collins. um through
you. I'm also have a question about
process and I am and have not seen this
done in my um five years on council now
but is there a possibility
um Charles that we could uh take this
one parcel out or um that we need to
really create a new definition for urban
farming from the sounds of the um
testimony and individuals we've heard
from tonight. And I I think that's going
to be a a larger conversation because I
think we have a lot of small homebased
businesses that may fall under that
urban farming
um definition
um that we may not be aware of
completely right now. I'm thinking
specifically about things like
beekeeping and um things like that that
produce other agricultural products. So,
um, is it possible to take out this one
parcel on, um, Mon on Monday at the
public service committee and move the
rest of the parcels forward while we
work on a definition for urban
agriculture?
>> Mr. U Brody, do you want to answer that
question from a legal perspective? we
should be able to divide the question
and move part forward and leave part or
I don't know if there's anything special
in an annexation ordinance that would
prevent that from happening.
>> Mr. Mayor John Brody, city attorney, um
you know, you know, on the fly, I don't
see anything problematic. Um I [snorts]
I guess I would note that there has been
more than one uh property owner that's
expressed some interest in in that. So I
I guess I would just leave that to the
council. It's certainly within your
discretion. Charles, did you have
anything?
>> Mayor, members of council, to Dr.
Aldrich, I just like to note that the
way the annexation will be written, the
ordinance, which up for referral, it
could be as simple as just deleting the
section and the referenced exhibit for
the annexation map
>> or could we divide that out?
>> That one I' I'd like to discuss with uh
city attorney Brody a little bit more
detail first how that would work.
>> Thank you, Dr. Aldridge. Anything more?
>> No, that's it. Thank you, sir.
>> Anybody else online?
Okay. Anybody else in the Dr. Emtts?
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, this bring I
the analogy that keeps coming to my mind
is the opportunity to make lemonade out
of lemons. You know, I do I think this
is kind of exciting that we could have
um some some really creative um
opportunities and solutions to this. And
I just want to say that as folks come
forward to the public service committee,
which we're going to want you to do to
help us with this, I would like to echo
back to Mr. nicely's comment about um
making sure that we are darn it I wrote
it down kind and respectful
and and I would like to add one more
thing in that that if we can all really
work on being kind, respectful and
trusting and I know that that can be
hard and don't roll your eyes can be
okay.
Um, you know, I I like the mayor said, I
don't think anyone wants any harm for
anybody in this situation. I've been in
the shop. I've purchased in the shop. I
appreciate the shop and the farm. Um,
but if we don't have some trust in this,
we're never going to get anywhere. So I
guess that that's part of what I would
ask from you all is that you trust us,
we will trust you and let's put our best
foot forward or we cannot we cannot and
just say well we all don't trust anybody
and this is going to you know go to hell
in a hand basket but I don't think that
that's going to get us anywhere. So I
would just ask that we all go forward on
a good foot that we're all looking for
solutions. So thank you.
>> Anybody else in the governing body? Mr.
Esabel.
>> Thank you Mr. Mayor through you. Um you
asked about advantages for annexation.
Well, this public service or public
hearing has given you a lot of uh
positive
uh feedback from people that didn't even
know about it there. So, the advertising
I guess that you you got from the public
hearing is going to increase your
business quite a bit from what I'm
seeing. Uh I for one uh if there was
ability for us to postpone it tonight
would support it.
>> Mr. Moody. Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Threeu. I want to first thank everybody
for your public comment. Again, I love
it when you know you uh testify as this
is your government. I just want for the
record, I have always voted no on forced
annexations. But if property owners want
it, then I'll vote I. And I do want to
see not only a uh potential amendment to
take out the parcel, but also from
another property owner's parcel. So, if
there's property owners in this
annexation that don't want to be in it,
please let us know. I definitely think
there should be an amendment there to
take them out. I don't see any issues
with that. And I would say as well, you
know, let's listen to our constituents.
If they're saying postponement, let's do
it. I think that's where the trust
issues coming from. We're not doing what
they say. Okay? So, let's make sure we
listen to them. They want postponement,
want an amendment, you know, let's do
the will of the people. Thank you,
>> Mr. Lelaymore.
[snorts]
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I can see that
the purpose of this public hearing has
been uh met tonight and I think that
that's the process that uh was
appropriately established
um by the state and by us.
I particularly recall the testimony from
Gay Woodhouse here uh because of how
longstanding this issue has been, how
difficult it's been, how it affects so
many people and has so many uh different
uh characteristics.
I I would say that I also um have been
supportive of these annexations
uh because all the services that we
provide and all the rights that people
have to their property uh they might
they need to be considered just as we
discussed tonight. So uh but I will say
I've never run up against this
particular situation before. It's unique
in my experience and I think probably in
the council's experience. So, um
hopefully Mr. Bloom here has some
concepts to bring forward. We we're not
going to be in a big hurry about this.
Um
I've heard over and over again the
questions are not being answered.
So,
we now have that opportunity to do that.
And I hope that whatever
Mr. Bloom comes up with for the next
meeting which will be the public service
uh next Tuesday
um will be distributed so people can
take a look at it and understand it. I
mean if this is all coming over the
Facebook and the internet um that's
pretty difficult for us to respond to.
It certainly is difficult for me. Um, I
can assure you that personally I haven't
been to the farm stand. I I didn't
>> Excuse me.
>> Uh,
please.
>> Hey guys, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa,
whoa, whoa.
>> Really? Excuse me. I I believe I have
the floor.
>> I'm taking it for just a second. Ladies
and gentlemen, we're not going to have a
this back and forth stuff, okay? So,
please, ma'am. Thank you very much. And
it's not in his word, it's in the
county. Thank you very much, Mr. Labour.
>> I'm darn interested. I can't wait to go.
I'm very interested in what Mr. Bloom is
going to come up with. But what bothers
me is we've been hearing, we've been
here for two hours.
We're listening.
The mayor here is taking copious notes.
And I in my thought process
I'm thinking that probably there are
other people who are grandfathered with
various kinds of uh livestock out in
that is has been brought into the city
that they might want to do the same
thing that they might want to start
looking at that. And certainly uh from
my perspective
uh
corporate agricultural
activities and corporate food production
is not a good thing and I welcome that
opportunity but it's got to fit within
the city
and it's got to it's got to be managed
and and I believe we're opening up a
different sort of land use
approval here. So, let's just be patient
a little bit and take a look at it
because I doubt this will be the last
one when I think about it. And I'm very
familiar with all these issues over many
years. Um, other people are going to
want to see what they can do on their
property. I think we've seen a vast
change in uh the ability of people to
market their own products over the past
10 or 12 years. I mean that progress is
not going to get stopped by us.
So I look forward to this discussion.
And I hope we can uh continue it. And I
and I I really wonder when you leave
tonight, I hope you think you got
listened to because you did.
And I also hope that you understand that
um the other property, the the
neighbors, the city regulations
are for the health, safety, and
protection of everyone.
and this has to fit into it. I think we
have learned. I know I have and I look
forward to uh that effort. But I hope
somebody's going to say on Facebook they
listen to us
and they want to answer our questions
because we did listen to you and we do
want to answer your questions and Mr.
Bloom and his office and his staff are
very interested in working on this and
working it through because we're going
to have other examples.
So, um
I
think I've said enough, Mr. Mayor. Thank
you.
Anybody else?
I'd like to say a few things. One is
thank you all. You guys did a great job.
You're respectful. you made your points
really clearly and um I think we have a
really clear understanding of your
passion for uh the quality of the food
that local farmers and dairy farmers and
and people bring and the value that it
brings to your lives. Um for me
personally, I think it's really
important that we work hard to try to
make sure that happens. And when I met
or talked with Tommy on the phone and
David on the phone, I've shared with
them that it's really important to me
that we find a way uh to do this. David,
I'm sorry that the postal service
screwed up your uh your notice, but the
purpose of notice is so that you can be
here to participate and these people can
be here and I think it was a rousing
success. So, I think the notice has been
good. Um while delayed, um it's here. Um
when we had great I I think I counted 30
some people who uh have spoken this
evening and I appreciate that. Um you
know, the first time I heard I didn't
know there was a farm stand on
Walteride.
didn't know it. I do now. Looking
forward to being a customer. Um,
I learned about this challenge uh on a
an email that I got from David on
January 28th. And since then, he and I
have talked on the phone, I think maybe
three times. We've texted each other.
We've uh we've emailed back and forth.
I've talked to his wife. Um,
they've really shared a lot with me on
what it is that they're concerned about.
Uh I had an hourlong meeting with uh my
chief building official and Charles
today to talk about you know how are we
going to define a farm? What can we do
to try to make sure that you know their
ongoing operations can uh can work
forward? And we will work really hard to
try to find a definition that um that
allows them to be successful in their
business. Uh, but I've also asked David
and Tommy to help me and to help the
governing body in telling us what is it
the things that that they do that is
important to share with us. You know, I
I I know now from talking to Tommy they
have chickens, they raised chickens for
meat, they raised chickens for eggs, um
they've raised some turkeys in the past,
she's had dairy cow. You know what what
are the things that you want to do um so
that we don't screw it up? So, it's it's
going to be incumbent upon you guys to
help us by by helping us define this by
sharing the things that are important to
you. What what do you do? What do you
grow? Um so that we can make sure we
find a definition that will help protect
those uses. And so it can't be just one
way where where we're sitting here
trying to come up with those
definitions. You have to be an active
part of that. And uh if you do that and
we do our side, we're going to we're
going to be we're going to come up with
a great uh definition and we're going to
come up with a way that can successfully
allow you to be successful in your
business. And so I would just ask you to
to help be part of that. Uh we'll work
really hard on our end to um um to be to
help you be successful. Again, I'm
looking forward to being a customer of
yours. Um and I hope that uh that you
have many many many years of success.
And with that, um, we'll say that the
purpose of the public hearing has been
met. And, uh, again, if you want to
continue this process, it'll be next
Tuesday, noon, here in this office,
right here in this room. Uh, we'll have
our next meeting. Uh, then the the
following Monday will be our our first
actual city council meeting where this
will be discussed and a motion would be
made whether or not uh, to move this
process forward. Okay. So, thank you all
for being here tonight. I really look
forward to uh uh continue to be part of
this with you and uh we'll hopefully get
to a point where we can be successful
together. Thank you.
Maybe we'll just take a fiveminut break,
let everybody clear out that wants to go
home because we're going to be here
another couple hours, I'm assuming, and
uh uh let the the council use the
restrooms if they need to.
>> Huh?
>> You're welcome.
>> But that's not what I was here.
Did you
>> We killed a bunch of bills
All
right, ladies and gentlemen, let's go
ahead and call this meeting back to
order, please. And thank you,
>> ladies and gentlemen. Let's call this
meeting back to order, please.
Let's call the meeting back to order,
please.
All right, we're back in order. Thank
you very much. Next item, please.
>> Next item is number A, ordinance, third
reading, creating chapter 1.28, 28
administrative inspection warrants,
establishing authority for their
issuance and amending the municipal code
of the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming to
authorize certain city officials as
specified to apply for administrative
inspection warrants.
>> All right. We have u an ordinance to
give the fire chief, fire marshall, and
the chief building official some limited
authority to use administrative
warrants, inspection warrants for four
items. And we'll go out to the audience.
Miss McCoy.
We're getting to be friends after all
this time
>> and we're going to be besties at the end
of this. I know it.
My name is Patricia McCoy and I am here
today to address a specific dangerous
loophole in section 1.28.020
B3. I know I'm repeating myself same as
every other meeting, but here we go
again. This section states that probable
cause shall be deemed to exist if an
inspection is reasonably necessary
necessary to determine, discover, or
verify the condition of a property. On
Friday, February 6, I sent each of you
an email containing a case law
supplement and strike sheet. I request
that these documents be entered into the
official record for this meeting. The
reason for this formal objection is
simple. Under article 1, section 4 of
the Wyoming Constitution, the words
determine and discover are a
constitutional non-starter. In Wyoming,
a warrant is a tool to verify a specific
pre-existing suspicion of a violation
that has been documented under oath. It
is not a license for the government to
enter a private home or business to
discover whether a violation exists. In
legal terms, that is an unconstitutional
fishing expedition. My attached
supplement cites the Wyoming Supreme
Court's ruling in Oil versus State,
which makes it clear that our state
constitution provides stronger privacy
protections than the Fourth Amendment.
It prohibits general warrants, the kind
that allow an official to enter for one
reason, and then spend their time
discovering other things to cite you
for. If an inspector does not already
have probable cause that a specific
violation exists, they have no business
asking a judge for a warrant to go
discover one. The strike sheet I
provided shows exactly how to fix this.
It's really, really easy. Remove two
words, determine and discover. Your
authority must be limited strictly to
verifying documented violations. We are
not uneducated on this matter. We know
that when a government official asks for
the power to discover conditions inside
private property, they're asking for a
skeleton key to our front doors. The
government exists to protect our rights,
not to create loopholes to bypass them.
So, I urge you to review the case law I
provided and close this loophole by
removing those two words before a vote
is taken on this ordinance. Thank you.
>> Miss McCoy, are you taking into
consideration the fact that um
>> you have to look at everything in this
ordinance, not just that one line
>> and Yes, sir. And that it it talks about
there's only four reasons we can ask for
this. There's only three people that can
do it. And it it so it's not a they
can't just go into your home because
they want to, right? it limits it to
only four things. So, does that help you
at all?
>> No, because those words are still there
and they can discover and determine
something else once they're already in
there because you left those words in
there. So, yes, while you limit why they
can request it, you don't stop them from
discovering or finding other things
while they're in there.
>> Thank you, Miss McQuay.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes.
>> Um, thank you, Mr. Mayor. you. Um I
while you're here, I would um like to
know from our attorney if you have any
issues, any constitutional concerns
regarding the words determine and
discover in B3.
>> Mr. Brody,
>> you missed it in a long time. You want
to I know you want to thank
>> itching. Um Mr. Mayor, John Brody, city
attorney. I I guess to answer your
question, um no, I don't have concerns.
I think you have to look through the
ordinance [snorts]
um
in parameteria. I hate to use Latin, but
that's, you know, they drill that into
our head uh when we're going through law
school. I think given the uh the four
things that the mayor um highlighted um
given the limited authority of those
officials and then given the
particularity requirements um that is in
both the fourth amendment and article 1
section 4, um it it doesn't give me
concern. I I respect her opinion, but uh
I disagree.
>> So, Mr. Mayor,
>> Dr.
>> for So, just for clarification, in your
legal opinion, when taken in its
entirety, those two words don't cause
you con cause you pause from a
constitutional issue with this
ordinance,
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor. No.
>> Thank you,
>> M. McCoy. Thank you very much.
>> No.
>> Okay,
>> your time's up. Thank you.
>> Of course.
>> Appreciate you being here tonight.
>> Mr. Brown,
>> welcome, sir.
>> Thank you. And good evening, uh, Mr.
Mayor and, uh, city council. Exward to
you. First off, I want to start off by
saying, you know, that we've had a lot
of great conversation over the last few
weeks on this. And so, I thank you for
taking the time to listen, not only just
listen, but to hear the people and hear
what they're saying. And I know there's
been a lot of um a lot of amendments, a
lot of suggestions on how to make this
better. And I actually want to
particularly thank uh Councilman
Lebornne and uh Councilwoman
um Aldridge uh for having the meeting
that we had last week with some of us in
in the community. I think we had a
really really productive conversation.
uh got really good understanding from
where everybody was at and a couple
things that came out of there just for
some language changes and also some
clarification.
Uh one area of contention was in
1.28.020
section B subsection 1. Uh there was a
lot of conversation hung up on area.
What is defined as area? So, put
together a little bit of a definition.
Had this kind of run through uh for uh
legal language and proposed this
amendment to add in there just so we can
take out some ambiguity. When the when a
judge looks at this, he knows the true
intent of what this ordinance is going
to do and what the true intent of the
area is. And it's for the purpose of
this ordinance. area is defined as a
large open space in a single commercial
or abandoned property and including
gathering areas, open office space,
parking areas, and the exterior
environment of a single parcel within
the single commercial or abandoned
property resides. And what that does, it
just it just cleans up the language. It
makes it a lot less ambiguous uh when
when they're trying to determine what
what are they discussing when it means
area. The other quick change is just a
small little one uh in that same section
subsection two where it talks about the
probable cause to to believe that the
condition of non-conformity violation or
other circumstances
requiring corrective action exists with
the respect to the designated property
or changing that or to and that causes
immediate risk to public health. I think
we we had a little bit of a discussion
on that and I believe it was brought up
that it initially was and and was
changed to or but uh we talked about,
you know, looking at changing it back to
and just to kind of tighten that
language up a little bit more in there.
And so those are the recommendations uh
that I'm I'm putting forth uh today. And
again, thank you for all the
conversation we've had over this. This
has definitely been a contentious issue
and I I do appreciate uh again
Councilman Lebornne and Councilwoman
Aldridge for taking that extra time cuz
I think we really working together with
the public really made this this
ordinance uh a lot more acceptable and
and and workable to where you have you
are able to meet your goal as well as we
continue to protect uh the rights of our
citizens. So, I think we we came pretty
darn close to a win-win on this one. So,
>> thank you.
>> Thanks for being here again,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> might I ask the city attorney about
those two points that were just raised
here?
>> Sure.
>> Do you believe that that explanation of
area is is legally adequate or do you
believe there should be any additional
language?
>> Mr. Mayor, John Brody, city attorney. I
I guess just having heard that language
for the first time tonight and not
really having looked at it or even had
the opportunity to think about it. Um I
really can't say for sure. Um we don't
have a definitions in the definition
section. Uh by virtue of that um most of
those words are going to give be given
plain meaning if a court were to look at
them. Um so that's I mean it's a policy
decision for for the uh city council. Um
Mr. Mayor um Mr.
>> [clears throat]
>> It might be a policy decision for the
city council and there might be a lot of
consideration here, but is that term
adequate [clears throat]
for the uh judge to determine the
location?
>> If I could follow up on that too,
because we've limited to those four
places, is that enough of a definition
of area?
>> Mr. Mayor. Um, what I would say is, you
know, people differ whether I think it's
appropriate to define area or not. Um,
it's going to depend on the judge or
whomever is, you know, supporting this
or attacking it. What I can tell you is
that I didn't define area.
So, from my perspective, it didn't need
a definition.
>> Thank you. And the question
>> the question of and or or
>> that was a direct policy call that the
uh public service committee made. They
considered whether it should be and you
voted to say no. You then voted to say
or. Um I've shared my concern about
inserting that language as as an and. I
think what it does is it tends to
collapse the exigency standard of when
no warrants are required into a process
that that is judicially created over you
know the long history of our country. Um
I think it creates more confusion. Um
but again that's a decision up to the
governing body.
[clears throat]
>> Um sir thank you. Um those are the
questions that came out of our meeting
and I believe that uh you certainly
answered them to my satisfaction in this
additional uh language is uh
unnecessary. Thank you.
>> Welcome back.
>> Hello again Kathy Sigleaniano. Um, I
guess kind of just a question or
clarification based off of what um,
Patricia McCoy asked and um,
Councilwoman Emmens and the attorney
discussed with the intent of determine
and discover um, if the intent isn't to
determine or discover anything further
when someone is in the property, then
what would it hurt to have those words
removed?
>> Thank you for commenting.
So on administrative warrants, are you
on that topic?
>> No,
not the subject. Yep.
>> We'll get there though.
Anybody else want to speak to us um on
administrative inspection warrants?
Um, good evening, council members and
Mr. Mayor. My name is Bailey Turner. Um,
and I guess my only question would be
for you to please specify what in the
ordinance
um, protects Wyoming residents and
private property owners.
Do you have a specific concern?
Not necessarily. No.
>> I mean, I think if I could answer that
question, we've tried to really limit
this to only three people can ask for
it. There's only four reasons they can
ask for this. It is if there's a fire
and we can't find the owner to be able
to do the inspection to find out what
caused that fire. Um, we're required
under the uh the fire code to do re uh
rout routine inspections for safety of
commercial properties, not not houses,
but commercial properties. And we have
to do those on a on a scheduled basis.
And um we try to get to them as often as
we can. Uh daycarees, you know, uh
nursing homes, things like that probably
get looked at more frequently than um
you know, my bicycle store did. So um do
that. Uh abandoned buildings, and we
have a definition of an abandoned
building. It's not a building that's
empty, but like if my dad is on uh on
vacation in Arizona for the winter,
that's not an abandoned building. It is
uh uh it's just unoccupied. Uh so we
have a specific definition of that. And
I'm having a brain fart for the the
fourth one, but we have four specific um
Oh, yeah. If you pull a building permit,
um, so you as the owner come in, pull a
building permit to do, uh, work on your
house, uh, you've got to let us finish
the inspections, um, to make sure that
what you did is, uh, to code and is safe
for you, but also the future people that
might live in that home. Those are the
only four reasons that we can ask for
administrative warrant. So, I think
we've narrowed it so tightly that uh, it
is a protection. It's a health and
safety issue. Uh, abandoned buildings
are bad for neighborhoods. Um, we don't
want to board one up if we think there
might be somebody inside it. The only
way we can know that is to go in and um
and and and look at it before we board
it up. I'd hate to board a building up
and leave someone inside. Um if we've
had a fire, I want to know, was it an
arson or was it just a tragic accident?
If we have an arsonist in town, I want
to know that so we can go get them. Um
if uh uh you pull a building permit and
you want to do work, I want to make sure
that the uh the work is done so that
future people that might live in that
home will be safe. And so I think that
is a protection for the residents of
Wyoming and the residents of Cheyenne.
>> I can completely respect that um answer.
My concern though is
why would it be necessary? Um,
in section 010B,
we have an abundance of
chapters and sections that are
already in place and these are the
processes by which we are already
following.
So
>> Bailey, I can answer that question for
you. Okay, I asked that exact same
question and and the all of those things
have a said these are your
responsibilities like the fire
department you're supposed to go and do
inspections and it says if you can't do
that you need to follow the rules of
your local municipality in order to get
compliance. So, we've passed the
International Building Code. We've
passed the International Fire Code, the
International Property Maintenance Code.
But what we haven't done is given those
people the next step to enforce those if
people will not allow them to do it. And
so, let's say that uh um we have a a
fire and we want to go in. If we don't
know who the owner is, we don't have the
right to go on that property and do the
inspection.
And I'll give you an example. We had one
just a couple months ago and an elderly
uh person was caught in a fire. Our
fireman rescued that person and we got
him out alive. Unfortunately, uh a
little while later, they succumb to
their injury and so he was not in a
position to give us permission to go on
the property when he was in the hospital
and now he's gone and we don't have a
building owner still in probate. We
cannot do that inspection.
>> I understand.
>> Yep. And and and the same thing with an
abandoned building. Uh we we don't it's
abandoned. we can't find the owner. We
need to board it up to keep transients
out so it's not a problem for your
neighborhood. But we can't find the
owner and so we're going to ask for a
warrant so we can go in and we can look
inside, make sure it's safe, and then
we're going to board it up to keep
people out to protect the neighborhood.
Um, if we have a responsibility to do
these safety inspections for the fire
department on commercial properties and
we find an owner that won't do that,
we're going to try really hard to
convince them and to educate them. and
talking to our fire chief, most of the
time over a period of months, we're able
to get them to say yes. But if we can't,
we have that responsibility. And those
things that you just quoted tell us that
we're supposed to give those people a
tool to make that enforcement if they
can't get compliance. Only if we can't
get compliance. We can't just go to the
judge and say, "We want to get in
there." They say, "Well, did you go talk
to those people?" Well, no. Well, you
need to go talk to them and we need to
take some time and uh and and get there
if that helps you. And that's and the
law I I looked at I I sat down with our
chief building official and asked him to
show me what this says and here's what
it says our responsibility is. And then
it says if you can't do that, you need
to use your existing rules and we don't
have a rule to do it. So we're adding
that rule.
>> Thank you. I uh very much appreciate
your explanation. Um
although these are not unique
circumstances and we have had people
pass away via fire or other um causes
and had the property be
unverified or however you want to word
this. Um there are processes in place
and at the last meeting the fire marshal
had said that he deals with these
circumstances quite often and it is very
rare that they have to extend themselves
in order to get compliance. and he said
just short of an administrative warrant,
meaning that would be the nail in the
coffin.
My concern is for residents of Cheyenne
who are unaware of
what's being presented to us. A lot of
people are in the dark.
Well, I would tell you, Bailey,
honestly, they'd have to be living under
a rock right now because of all the the
social media that's been going on on
this, all the uh um the things that have
been happening in in I mean, the Cowboy
State Daily and um all the news, the
newspaper, it's been front page on the
newspaper. There's been a ton of uh of
coverage on this item. And you're
probably right, there are people who out
there that don't know. We I'll ask you
this. How how should we fix that
problem? Don't don't residents have some
responsibility to know what's going on
in their community?
>> I believe that this ordinance is
completely unnecessary and should be
tabled. I do not think it should move
forward. I think the process is in place
is a structural issue within
how we're governing ourselves and it's
not up to the council to
administer power where they don't
already have it. It's needs to be
structurally
confronted and
revised. Bailey, I appreciate that. But,
you know, we live in a representative
government where you elect people to
make decisions that are in the best
interest of of the folks who live here.
And um you know, so I think that that's
what this governing body is trying to do
is to exercise the responsibility they
have to um take care of these four
issues that I hope will only happen
maybe once or twice a year. And I I pray
that we don't have people get passed
away in fires. Uh we're really good at
getting there as quick as we can. um you
know that people will will work with us
when we need to do um inspections. Uh
that we don't have any more abandoned
buildings, but I think we're going to
have some more. Um but that's why we
have a representative government and
when our staff comes to us and says,
"You've given us half of the loaf, but
we need the other half in order to be
able to do our jobs." That's what this
representative government's trying to
do. But I do appreciate your thoughts on
policy. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Sir.
>> Uh, good evening, Mayor and Council. Um,
my I needed some clarification on
>> your name again.
>> Oh, yeah. Sorry. My name is uh Mr.
Matthews. I'm local here in Cheyenne.
I'm a business owner as well. Now, I
read this proposed ordinance a while
back and I didn't make it to the last
meeting here or at the council and I
was, you know, I regret that, but at the
same time, I've had a lot of different
um interpretations from other people and
I kind of want some clarification
on um at home businesses. So, what I'm
what I'm hearing is that doesn't apply
to your residents and if your businesses
is registered at your house that they
can have those warrants. Say if someone
reported there's a fire and then you
know there's a fire going on, can those
you know people come in to your home
even though your business is registered?
>> I promise you sir if your house is on
fire, we're coming in. We're going to
put that fire out. We're going to rescue
you. We're going to rescue your animals.
We're going to put that fire out, make
that property safe, and then we're going
to leave.
>> Absolutely.
>> Yep. Okay.
>> Guarantee you. You call 911 or your
neighbor calls 911 or what fireman sees
it, we're going to put that fire out. No
question at all. Whether you're a home,
a business, a doghouse, it doesn't
matter. We're putting it out, sir.
>> Absolutely. And then uh just a little
more curious on the inspection side of
things. Say if you have a business
registered at your home residence and uh
is there I've heard a lot of different
things, so I'm just clarification. Will
you need uh need those inspections? And
is there any way I've heard that you
they can just come in and inspect at
will, you know, for annually? I'm
assuming that's wrong. I just wanted to
verify this. You know, I don't know
about a home business, but our fire
chief is sitting over there and our fire
marshall is sitting over there and we're
going to ask him that question and get
you the correct answer because I do not
know that answer.
>> Okay.
>> But, um, hang loose. He's right behind
you. Give him the microphone.
Uh, mayor, councel, Bob Mason, uh, fire
marshall. I can clarify that. The only
the only residences that we that we
inspect are homes that have businesses
in them that require licensing that
require an inspection, like a home
daycare or a developmental disabilities
home. Um, there have been some other
home businesses that have required
licensing that we do do go inspect. when
that license typically comes up
typically not even for renewal other
than daycarees or the DDD facilities.
But um
>> would a would a tattoo parlor in home or
a massage parlor qualify?
>> I mean if that if that I don't know that
we've inspected any home tattoo parlors,
but if it requires a license, and I
believe it does, we we the clerk's
office will typically have us go by
there and do a fire inspection. Yep.
>> As part of that license approval.
>> Thank you, sir. Did that answer your
question?
Yes, sir. It did. And I want to say
thank you everyone for hearing me. And
I'm sorry for the uh before. I just want
to say thank you so much.
>> We're happy that you're here. It doesn't
matter. Appreciate you.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Anybody else want to speak to
this administrative inspection warrant
on third and final reading?
>> Jennifer,
>> thank you.
>> Uh Gary, you can go ahead and unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you, Mayor Collins. Gary Chadwick,
Shine Board of Realators President.
However, I haven't had a meeting to
actually speak on behalf of Shine Board
of Realators. So, I'll be just talking
for myself. Um, I want to thank the
council, uh, public service committee
staff, and the attorney for all the work
that they've done on this. I think it's
a very good bill now, and uh, the
substitution was a lot of work, and they
spent a lot of hours. And I would like
to go ahead and see you pass it on third
reading today,
>> Carrie. Thanks for being here tonight,
Jennifer.
>> Uh, Mr. Miller, you can go ahead and
unmute yourself.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Oh, looks like Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you just fine, sir.
>> Oh, okay. All right. Um,
sorry. Give me here.
>> See, that's why I write that's why I
write stuff down. Don't use technology.
I can find it quick.
>> Oh, yeah. I'm shuffling through all my
paperwork right now. Okay. Uh
>> um Okay.
Um I'm speaking tonight to address the
viability of this ordinance. Regardless
of your intent, a law is only as good as
its ability to survive a courtroom
challenge. Right now, section 1.28.020
B3 contains a fatal defect that
compromises the entire chapter. The
poison pill threatens viability. that
that section currently authorizes
warrants to determine, discover, or
verify the condition of a property.
Verify is a viable legal standard. It
means you have evidence and are
confirming it. Discover is a
constitutional non-starter. It creates a
general warrant, a fishing expedition
authorized by the government to find a
crime it doesn't know exists. If you
pass this text as written, you are not
creating a tool for your inspectors. You
are creating a target for litigation.
Any defense attorney will look at the
word discover site obover state and move
to have the entire ordinance declared
void abinio invalid from the start. You
risk wasting months of staff time and
thousands in legal fees defending a
single word that you don't even need.
The fix a surgical amendment to ensure
this ordinance remains viable and
enforceable. I ask for a surgical
amendment. Strike the words determine,
discover, or leave the word verify. By
removing the unconstitutional language,
you inoculate the ordinance against
immediate legal challenge. You keep the
tool your inspectors need, verification,
while removing the liability that will
kill the statute. Finally, to guarantee
the long-term viability of this program,
I ask you to add a sunset clause. Set
this ordinance to expire automatically
on February 9th, 2028,
uh, unless reauthorized by a vote. This
creates a mandatory viability audit. It
forces a future council to review this
the incident reports mandated in section
two. If the data shows the law is
working safely, you renew it. If it
shows abuse, it expires. Don't pass a
law that is designed to fail. Protect
the viability of your of your work.
Strike the discovery loophole and add
the sunset clause. Um there there's also
um uh additionally uh likely uh because
you've been notified, there's likely
going to be liability uh personally of
each of the voting members that vote yes
to this. Thank you.
>> Sir, come on up.
So you it was worth staying around,
right?
>> Uh Mr. Mayor, Council, um sorry, I don't
know which shirt I was supposed to wear
for this one. So,
>> ju just tell us your name. We'll love
you anyways.
>> Uh, I'm Steven Love. Um, I'm a homeowner
in W one. Um,
I I just have some uh some questions
about this. Um, if I can. Um, I had some
concerns. Um, you mentioned arson. Um,
why why wouldn't you not be able to
already get a warrant for an arson
investigation? Wouldn't you be able to
get a criminal warrant for that?
I I think we can ask our attorney, but
if we know it's arson, we can we can
probably do that, but we don't know. And
we have to have permission to get on a
private property. Um, and if the owner
is dead, we don't have the ability to do
that. And so, we're looking for a tool
to be able to get on and and discern
whether or not something malicious
happened or if it was just a horrible
accident that caused that to happen.
>> So, I guess that uh kind of leads into
my second question. Um, is is that um
is that the spirit of this um
legislation? Is that we're re you're
really more concerned about those fringe
cases or is this going to be used as a
tool um I guess frequently is my
concern. You know, we got te we had
testimony um from our fire chief and
from the chief building official that uh
typically when they find somebody
doesn't want to give them permission to
do that, uh it just takes a little bit
of uh a relationship and and to share
with them the reasons they're doing it,
the authority they have to do it. And
almost without exception, I wouldn't say
100% but almost without exception,
eventually they get compliance. And so
our guys are really good at uh at
sharing the reasons. And uh so my my
feeling would be will exist very very
rarely. Um but it is a tool that we
would like to have uh for those cases
where we just can't get there.
>> Okay.
>> And a perfect example is an abandoned
building.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, we we don't have an owner. We
can't identify an owner or they're out
of state. We send them letters. They
don't answer back and we really want to
get in and close that up for the
neighborhood. Um you know, I I can see
us using it for that purpose. Uh we'll
we'll go to the property. We'll put a
posting on there. We'll uh we'll go on
social media if we can find the owner
and go to them that way. We'll send them
a certified letter, but if they don't
respond, what do we do? And for me, not
doing anything is not an option. And so,
we would like to be able to go in, make
sure that it's safe to board the
building up, then we can board it up and
we can maintain that and make it safer
for the neighborhood. So, those are just
a couple examples where I I could see
that we would use it. But, uh, when it
comes to the inspections and stuff,
we've had really good luck at convincing
people that, you know, it's it's okay
that we're not in there to do nefarious
things. We just want to make sure it's
safe.
>> Um, so you'll have to forgive my
ignorance.
>> And by the way, that's only for
commercial buildings that we do.
>> Right. Um, is there anything in here?
Um, I'm sorry. I've very briefly read
it, so you'll have to forgive my
ignorance. But is there anything in
there saying that okay, we've notified
them by phone and email and we've made
three attempts or five attemp?
Yeah, we have to get we have to make
numerous attempts and and the ordinance
does state what that is before we can
even go to the judge and then the judge
is supposed to ask us to tell them what
what efforts did we make? Did you send
the certified letters? Did you do all
the things you're supposed to do? So,
yes, sir.
>> Um
and then can you say that this won't be
used for code inspections on private
residences?
>> Um when you say code inspections,
>> um
>> like their grass is too long or uh their
house is
like let's say um
their outlets aren't uh to to code.
>> Yeah. So, the ordinance says
specifically you can only do this for
four reasons and we talked about those.
An abandoned building, uh an inspection
after a fire, commercial properties that
have um a requirement to be inspected.
Um and then the last one is if the owner
pulls a building permit, then we're
going to go in and inspect the work that
was done. um those are the only four
issues that they can come. So to answer
your specific question, no, we cannot
and will not uh go into your home
because it's old and and maybe doesn't
have all the the modern recruitments
that a new house would have, that's not
allowed under this ordinance.
>> So along those lines, if you do go in to
inspect that work and they do discover a
code violation, um what happens then?
Um, I believe that uh uh and we can ask
Tono this, but you know, just because an
old house doesn't meet the modern code,
um it doesn't have to be brought up to
uh to code. There's nothing that says
you have to do that. They're they're
protected. And he's walking up here now.
We'll get him to uh to tell you that for
sure.
[snorts]
>> Miss Parmlo, thank you for being here.
>> Mayor Collins, Tony Parmlo, chief
building official, city of Cheyenne. um
through you. Um the spirit and the
intent of all of the adopted codes for
the city uh do not require or mandate
that the building department would be
going in to existing homes looking for
anything that is not current code
compliant. Uh in the event that a
building permit is pulled for a project,
um the department might see that
something is not code compliant in a
existing portion of the home. There's no
requirement upon our our department to
bring that up to code, nor would any be
placed on a homeowner, but we do take
the opportunity to advise if we see a
life safety issue, but that's purely
advisement. It is the way we handle
those. So, I hope that answers the
question for you, sir.
>> So, Tona, would that be like you uh you
hire an electrician to put a fan in or
something like that? You would inspect
the the work that was licensed and
permitted, but nothing else.
>> Uh, Mr. Mr. [snorts] Mayor, that's
absolutely correct, sir. We would not be
going into the kitchen or bedrooms or
anything else trying to look at outlets
or anything like that, sir.
>> Does that help, sir?
>> Yes. Thank you. I think that's all I
have for you. Thank you.
>> You sure?
>> Okay. Thanks for being here.
Anybody else here to speak to uh
administrative warrants?
>> Tamara,
>> Mr. Hill,
>> mayor, council, Tamara Trir, award one.
I just have a quick question as to I
mean after I've listened for numerous
days just like all of you guys there was
an example that out of the 12 years
they've had to do this maybe five times
in government I've learned that we don't
make laws unless we really need to. And
out of 12 years to have five incidents
that's kind of ridiculous to make a law
that people don't want and actually
don't need just to make somebody's life
a little bit easier to do their job. My
question is, if there's a fire, why can
we not hold the property for 10 to 15
days and then release it back to the
person? I mean, that would be an easy
fix if you're looking for that. And then
make the bill specific to abandoned
buildings. I asked for this to be tabled
from the beginning and I'm still asking
for it to be tabled again. Thank you.
>> Can you answer the question? I mean, I
think we have the right to go on
property when there's an emergency, but
when the emergency is completed, I don't
know that we have the right to hold the
property. Sir,
>> Mr. Mayor, I I guess I would just say if
if there's a suspicion of of criminal
activity on the property. Um, you know,
there's there's case law of support
holding that that property in sort of a
um frozen state while you secure a
judicial warrant. Um, but I was in that
I I don't know how I don't know how that
approach deals with the situations where
a a house is burned down and you don't
know why.
>> Yep.
Thank you, Jennifer.
>> Mr. or Ellen S from Ward 2, you can go
ahead.
>> Mr. Sheldon, welcome.
>> Yeah, Alan Sheldon, Ward 2. Um, thank
you for the opportunity to speak this
evening. I'll keep it brief since we've
already been on this for a while. I
think the substitute is definitely
better than the original. Uh, but like
some of the others that spoke before me,
I also dislike the words determine and
discover in 1.28.020B3.
Um, if the city attorney is not
concerned about these words, uh, then
would the council be okay with removing
the words in an amendment this evening?
I think uh a few small updates in good
faith could go a long way to removing uh
any remaining public opposition. Thank
you.
>> Thank you, Jennifer. Do you have any
more?
Last opportunity for people in the
audience to speak to us on the the
public side of this comment.
All right, hearing no more, we'll go to
Dr. Emmens for a motion.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so move
>> seconded by Mr. Crave. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by substitute
dated February 5th, 2026.
The substitute includes changes from the
presented January 30th, 2026 sub,
including the definition of abandoned bu
buildings and the limits on warrants in
four areas, including one, abandoned
buildings. Two, building permits pulled
by the owner or their agent allows the
chief building off official to inspect
the work to make sure it is too code and
does not cause a safety issue.
Three, fire investigations after the
emergency is over. When the owner of the
building can't be found or won't allow
the investigation.
Four, annual fire inspections of
commercial buildings as required by the
fire code. These are done on a scheduled
on a schedule determined by the risk the
building or business has for fires. The
substitute also includes amendments made
and recommended by public service
committee on February 2nd, 2026.
An amendment to add section two and
reumber to read in quotes and incident
report will be provided to the city
council following each executed
administrative inspection warrant.
In amendment
section 1.28, 28.20B 20B item number one
to read reasonable legislative or
administrative standards for conducting
a routine periodic or area inspection of
commercial properties are satisfied with
respect to the particular commercial
property or reasonable legislative or
administrative to a property subject to
inspection pursuant to a permit as
described in section 1.28.010
C3 of this chapter
and amendment section 1.28.020B
item number two to read. There is
probable cause to believe that a
condition of nonconformity,
violation, or other circumstance
requiring corrective action exists with
respect to the designated property or
that causes an immediate risk to public
health and or safety or
>> might be the longest amendment we've
ever had. So, thank you for doing that.
So, well, is there a second? Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave.
All right, we'll go back out to the
audience on the amendment. Uh,
>> there was just a couple of uh um of
changes. Anybody in the audience want to
speak to those changes?
>> How about from
Mayor Collins? I would move
>> Mayor Collins, I would move to amend the
substitution, please.
>> Go ahead. Second.
>> What's your amendment?
My amendment would be to uh remove and
to change on number 120.280 280
um
uh 20 to uh B2 to remove to change the
word or the sec the first uh or to and
so it would read that uh there is
probable cause to believe that a
condition of nonconformity violation or
other circumstance requiring corrective
action exist with respect to the
designated property and that causes an
immediate risk to public health or
safety.
Second,
>> Mr. Mayor, hang on just a second. I got
to write this down or I'm going to get
behind himself and I'm going to be in
trouble. So,
all right, we have an amendment to the
amendment. Um, and so we'll go out to
the audience on changing the word or to
and.
Jennifer
Uh, Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
[clears throat]
>> Um, I'm I'm actually just trying to
process that. If there's anybody else
that could go before me, I probably just
need a a three minute window of time.
>> Anybody else?
>> Uh, Alan Sheldon, you can go ahead if
you'd like.
>> Yeah, I just want to say that or Alan
Sheldon, W 2. Um, I support the
amendment.
>> Thank you, Alan. Mr. Miller.
All right, we're going to close public
comment and we'll go to the governing
body. Uh, Mr. Wolf,
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you through you. I'd
speak on and against the amendment. Um I
um I don't think actually it's even
germanine to this bill this uh proposed
ordinance uh because we already have the
authority to act when there is an
immediiacy
>> uh and to insert an and there will
simply both create conditions of
confusion
uh and um it uh it is not uh at all
necessary for all of the other powers
that we have for immediate uh imminent
uh threats. So, um it's not gerine. Uh
and I would urge the body to vote no.
Thank you,
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Um thank you, Mr. Mayor. to the council.
Could you explain one more time about
why what that potentially does for a
legal what legal ramifications there are
for that?
>> Mr. Brody, the exagent [clears throat]
that
>> Mr. Mayor, excuse me, John Brody, city
attorney. Um, I guess my concern uh with
the approach is that it collapses what's
called the exigency doctrine into a
[snorts] judicial process for issuing it
well for applying for and receiving
warrants to be issued by the court. Um,
the whole point of that that doctrine is
that there are uh circumstances
including when there's immediate risks
of harm um where um you don't need to
get a warrant. So what this is doing is
conflating these two different
doctrines. One being an exception to the
warrant requirement, the other being
this warrant requirement that you know
that we all appreciate and that we all
um
we all are aware of. Um and I think it
confuses the issue, but certainly it is
a policy uh decision up for the
governing body and whether or not you
want to uh kind of insert that exigency
idea into a warrant proposal. Um, I
would have concerns, but ultimately it's
not my decision.
>> So,
>> Dr. Evans,
>> Mr. Mayor, for just for clarification,
does it um dilute the authority,
>> Mr. Mayor? I I
it's hard to see into the future. I
guess I I I I can't see how they would
seek an administrative warrant if
there's an immediate risk to someone in
the community. they would just go in and
address that risk as they are allowed to
under the exigency doctrine.
>> Dr.
>> So, uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor. So, just
for clarification, it doesn't help. I
mean, it it basically takes away what
we're trying to do,
>> Mr. Mayor. I I think it kind of depends
on your policy perspective on this
ordinance as a whole, but I I think from
a legal perspective, um modifying uh
paragraph 2 to create an immediate risk
requirement, um I think it largely just
negates paragraph 2 and
>> I might as well not even be in there.
>> Thank you.
>> Anyone else on the on the amendment?
>> Mr. Mayor, Dr. Renie.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> I have a question. So, and probably for
Mr. Brody too. I um did not support the
and language in committee because when I
read this, it seems to say to me that
with if you add and in there, it means
that it requires corrective action
[snorts] um
with respect to the designated
properties and that causes an immediate
risk, which means that and I think
that's maybe what Mr. Brody was saying
in legal language, but to me it says
that not only does it might require
corrective action, but it has to pro has
to um
has to be a cause of immediate risk to
public health. Well, to me then that
precludes us if there's an abandoned
building
um it's not necessarily immediate risk
till it catches fire. Then it becomes an
immediate risk and then we don't need
the the administrative warrant. So if
somebody's has an open building permit
and they're not allowing inspection
because they're doing something because
this developer and
I think people understand this is not
always aimed at the the single
individual. There are some disreputable
builders in town. um if that builder is
doing something that's not legal or not
safe and is not allowing inspection,
um you know, it needs to be inspected
because it could potentially become an
immediate risk. But to me, by putting
and in there, it couples it together
that not only does it have to have a
potential problem, but it has to be an
immediate problem in order to do it. And
that's the way I read it and that's the
way I posed it because
and maybe
And I know this is longwinded and I
apologize, but so Mr. Can Mr. Brody
explain the way I read it. Is that
correct? And if it and is that what he's
trying to say in legal language with the
exit agency?
>> We have the civilian side, the legal
side. Do you agree,
>> Mr. Mayor? Yes. [clears throat] And
maybe I wasn't articulate enough on that
point. I I think it's two things, right?
It it seems to add another element into
what um probable cause requires, right?
you have to have what Dr. Renie just
referred to and then secondarily I think
it raises that concern with exigency and
that and that doctrine that is sort of
the exception to warrants. Um so yes
>> thank you.
>> Well Mr. Mayor, if I can conclude, the
reason I oppose the change to end and I
I guess I still will is that if and
especially in the case of abandoned
buildings, if if it has to be an
immediate risk before we can do an
inspection, then by the time it becomes
an immediate risk, I think it's too
late.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> All right. The motion is to change or to
and. Did you have another one, Jennifer?
>> I just wanted to make sure Dr. Aldridge
doesn't want to speak again.
>> No, I'm good. Thank you.
>> The motion is to change or to and. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed,
>> no.
>> No.
>> Dr. Rainey is a no. Dr. Emmens is a no.
Mr. Wolf is a no. Mr. Crave is a no. Mr.
White, Mr. Escoel, and Mr. Leborn and
myself are nos. The uh amendment fails.
Dr.
>> Mr. Mayor, I would move to amend.
>> Go ahead.
>> On uh B
uh three of 1.28.020,
I would like to uh remove determine,
discover, or
>> second.
>> So, I heard you ask why they're able to
do this. They're members of the
governing body. They're just not here
today.
All right, we'll go out to the audience.
I think we already know your opinion.
You've asked for it to be removed. Um,
do we need to say any more from your
side?
>> Mr. Sheldon.
>> Actually, it's Mr. Miller.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Uh, yep. Can you hear me?
>> We can, sir.
>> Okay. So, I got about three minutes
here. Uh, seems like this is going
pretty uh quickly. I I don't understand
uh how a normal public body is supposed
to have any kind of real uh commenting
ability when you guys are spitfiring
everything so quickly. But uh but here's
what I've got. Um uh okay. So you've got
a surgical amendment. Uh is is this
correct? Striking determine and
discover. Is that is that correct?
>> Affirmative.
>> Okay. Um all right. So uh
yeah, the previous amendment regarding
and was a policy debate. This amendment
regarding discover is a constitutional
necessity. Councilwoman Aldrich has just
offered this body a liability shield. By
moving to strike determined and
discover, she is removing the poison
pill that makes this ordinance void
abinio. If you vote yes on this
amendment, you keep the word verify.
Your inspectors can still do their jobs.
You lose nothing but the liability. If
you vote no, you're going on the record
right now stating that you insist on the
power to conduct general warrants to
discover violations you don't know
exist. Mr. Brody may tell you he has no
concerns, but Mr. Brody will not be the
one named in the 42 USC 1983 civil
rights lawsuit. You will. Councilwoman
Aldrich is offering you the safe path.
Take it, strike the words, keep verify,
and pass a constitutional law. Thank
you,
>> ma'am.
Welcome back, Bailey.
>> Bailey Turner. Yes, I am just in support
of this amendment to strike. Thank you.
>> Thank you. I'm starting to remember some
of these names. Anybody else in the
audience?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Hi, I'm Kristen Turner and I also will
like to put my name on here to strike
that as well. I do not agree and I wish
there was more people to um voice this
because our voices need to be heard.
>> Thank you, ma'am. Appreciate you being
here this evening. It's been a long
night.
Anybody else?
All right. We'll go to the the governing
body. Anybody on the governing body
wants to speak to this? The motion is to
remove um determine um and discover.
Mr. Wolf.
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you uh through you. I
am speaking on and against the
amendment. Uh I think that whatever we
have heard from Mr. Miller is probably
not the state of the law. Uh I don't
think we're assuming any liability by
taking an action on this. Um I've
actually litigated uh 14 42 1983 cases.
Um, and uh, I don't think uh, I don't
feel any need to go out and buy a whole
bunch of uh, liability insurance uh, for
a vote I'm going to cast against this.
So, thank you, Mayor.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
Jennifer.
>> Uh, Dr. Aldrich, you can go ahead.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Thank you, Mayor Collins. you. First and
foremost, I just want to say that um if
our goal is really um with building
permits, especially to verify the
condition of the property or structures
for compliance with applicable law, as
is stated in B3,
um I'm not sure that determine or
discover really add anything uh to that
section. Um, and I think that, um, we
have worked really hard on this, uh,
ordinance and making sure that, um, it's
something that our community can live
with. I think this is a a minor change
that, uh, still allows the city to be
able to do what uh, we're claiming we
want to do, which is to be able to
verify the condition of a property or
structures for compliance with the uh,
through the permit process. So, I would
encourage my colleagues to vote um in
favor of this amendment.
>> Anyone else?
All right, we have a motion to strike
determined and discover. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> Now,
>> may I see the hands or the nose? Okay.
Dr. Emmens, Mr. Wolf, Mr. Caggrave, and
Mr. Laybourne. This uh amendment passes.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Do you have any more?
>> Uh, nope. That's it, sir.
>> Okay. Thank you very much.
>> All right. We're on the substitute. Um,
>> mayor.
>> Yes.
>> I have an amendment, Mr. Mayor.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. for
you. On um page four
B, probable cause shall be deemed as if
the public is following it. On um number
one
after where it says of this chapter, I'd
like to add in and I'll go slow, Mr.
Mayor. I know you have to write it down.
For the purpose of this ordinance,
area
is defined as
any large open space
in a single
commercial
or abandoned property. comma.
and
includes gathering
areas,
comma,
open office space, comma,
parking areas, comma,
and the
exterior environment
of the single parcel
within which
the single
commercial
or aband property resides.
>> Mr. Mayor, just a point of order.
>> M.
>> These speaking amendments are really uh
just a very inefficient way to do this.
I mean, if if Councilman Moody had an
amendment like this, they could have
spent 10 minutes typing it up and giving
it to us instead of reading a full
paragraph of amendments. And I just
object as a matter of process that uh we
have really added to the lack of
efficiency in reviewing an ordinance
that has spent this is our sixth hearing
on this and here we are at 9 almost 9:15
at night. Uh and uh we have a speaking
amendment. Um so I I would ask that it
not be entertained. Thank you, Mr.
Mayor.
arbitrator procedure. Uh there's nothing
Robert's rules of war says you can't do
this.
>> It's my decision to make that and I
would agree that you you have the right
to make this amendment, but I think as a
courtesy to your fellow council people,
having something in writing that they
could read would be a little bit uh
easier to uh to do. And I just want to
ask you, does is the rest of the
paragraph uh stay as it is?
>> Yeah, it's just Okay.
>> All right. And Dr. Alders, did you
second that? Did I understand?
>> Yes, I second that.
All right, we'll go out to the audience.
We have a definition of area. Miss
Bailey, welcome back.
Um, Bailey Turner. Yes. I would just
like to support the amendment and also
state that
the ordinance is not wanted and if we
could just table it,
we would have saved six meetings and
weeks of time on something that is
completely unnecessary.
Thank you.
>> Anyone else? Jennifer. M
>> Mr. Miller, I'm going to give you
permission to unmute yourself. There we
go.
>> Mr. Miller, welcome back.
>> Uh, mayor, council, uh, I'm speaking in
strong support of Councilman Moody's
amendment to define the term area. I
also need to address the objection
raised by Councilman Wolf regarding the
inefficiency of this process.
>> Sir, let's talk. Let's stay on the
motion. Okay. We've already ruled on
that. We've already ruled on it. It's
moving on. Okay.
>> Okay. Okay. Okay. Uh well, so uh back in
reference to Councilman Moody's, uh
definition, without it, the word area is
a blank check. An inspector could claim
an area inspection covers an entire
neighborhood or the interior of a
private back office.
>> Mr. Miller, have you read the ordinance,
sir?
>> Uh yeah, but I'm I'm speaking in terms
>> No, no. Have you read the ordinance?
>> Yes.
>> And doesn't it restrict it to only four
things? So how can it be a whole
neighborhood, sir? The ordinance
specifically says there's only four
things you can do.
>> Well, actually, uh, I'm I'm actually not
here to debate with you necessarily as
much as to get my point on record.
>> Well, okay, go right ahead, sir.
>> Um, by defining it effectively as large
open spaces, parking lots, and
exteriors. Uh, Councilman Moody is
drawing a box. He's telling the
inspectors exactly where they can look
and more importantly where they cannot.
Ambiguity is the best friend of
government overreach. If you leave area
undefined because you are tired and want
to go home, you are inviting a lawsuit
down the road where a judge will have to
define it for you. Do the work tonight
and define the term. I urge you to
ignore the complaints about the clock.
Vote yes on the Moody amendment. Lock
down the definition of area so there is
no confusion later. Thank you.
>> Jennifer.
>> Uh Mr. Sheldon.
>> Mr. Sheldon, welcome back.
Oh,
>> Mr. Sheldon.
>> That's me. Sorry.
>> He's She's trying to unmute you, sir.
>> They swapped too fast.
>> That's all right. Uh, yeah, Alan
Sheldon, W 2. Um, I support U. Mark
Moody's amendment. Um, I think it's
rarely a bad thing to have things
defined. Thank you.
>> I like being succinct. Thank you, sir.
>> Anybody else in the audience on the
amendment for Mr. Moody that defines
area?
Nobody. All right, we'll go to the
governing body. Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, so many ideas.
Um, first of all, so I'm going to urge
my fellow council members to vote
against this amendment. One,
the fact that it deals with parking lots
makes no sense whatsoever. That that
makes no sense. Yeah, it's in their
mark. It says parking lots. That makes
no sense whatsoever. Um the whole when
you read the amendment, it it is
ridiculous. It makes no sense.
>> Um so I think as our attorney explained,
area is a common language word approved
in legal processes. every word in a
document does not need to be defined.
The fact that we've identified the four
specific areas that this covers in
itself nails down the area. So, I would
strongly uh re encourage my council
members to vote no. And I think it is
very concerning that other people seem
to understand what this amendment says,
but we don't.
Mr. Mayor, Dr. Renie,
>> Dr. Renie, sir.
>> Yeah, Mr. Mayor. My understanding when
when we went through this in public
service committee was that
um
this generally referred the only time we
do areawide inspections. And that's why
we limited commercial property was the
fire department under fire code has to
do inspections, routine inspections of
commercial property.
And I brought up the point as a business
owner in the years I'd had my in the
20ome years I had my business I had you
know been inspected twice. They came in
make sure that
that my fire extinguisher was was up to
date working properly that I had fire
doors where I was supposed to have them
that my fire doors weren't propped open.
Um, and so basically things that I would
think my patients would want to know
were being taken care of and taken care
of properly. Um, so I guess I don't
perhaps the my colleague from Ward three
that made the motion can explain
um
because that's what these inspection
area inspections are used for and it's
within the fire code and and we related
it only to commercial properties and I
don't think most and as a as a as a
business owner I don't think we should
have an objection to those of
those uh inspections and I don't think
our clients, customers or patients I
think they would want to know that when
they're visiting our offices that
they're safe. Um, so I guess I'd like to
explanation from my colleague how
how his definition works better when
we're considering we're not we're
talking about areawide
um fire inspections that are underneath
the fire code.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Threw you.
Uh, thanks for that question. I'm
looking at is just a way to protect
residential properties. That's why uh
added in here. It's pretty defined.
Again, it says single commercial or
abandoned property and includes
gathering areas and that because again
it does give a little bit of that broad
spectrum for inspections but also to it
adds an additional layer to protect
residential properties. That is why I
motion for this.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. or Dr. Renie. So I guess I really
don't understand the need for it because
B1 line two middle of it says of
commercial properties. So it doesn't
give the ability for area inspections of
residential properties. So
um I guess I think the motion is
probably redundant. Mr. Mayor,
>> thank you. Anybody else in the governing
body? Jennifer,
>> Dr. Eldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I just wanted to
respond to uh Councilwoman Imman's
comment that um people seem to know
about this definition. I I the first
time I heard this was actually this
evening when um a gentleman stood up and
read it earlier. Um I think it simply
defines area. Um I think that um it the
real concern I think has been in in
hearing what people have said over the
last few weeks of making sure that area
is defined um to just that one um parcel
or building. And so um tonight was the
first time I've heard that u proposed
amendment. Um but I think it's just a
reassurance of uh by defining that the
word area. So, uh, for that reason, I'll
be voting, uh, yes on this amendment
tonight. It may seem redundant. Um, I I
would remind everyone that there are
times when we have businesses like child
care, uh, providers who do business in
their home where this could be um,
extended to that uh, part of the home
that's used as a business. And I think
that Councilman Laybourne uh referred to
that um has referred to that as well
that you know there are some homes that
do have businesses in them that do
require inspections and so um it would
be that part of the home that is being
used for business um which may be some
of the concern about uh limiting or
defining area.
>> Anyone else in the governing body? Mr.
labor. [clears throat]
>> Mr. Mayor,
since
my name and my business was brought up,
I think this might give some
reassurance.
>> [snorts]
>> I'm glad to have the fire inspectors
come
and take a look at uh my wife's child
care in the business of our in the
basement of our home.
And you know what they do? They come
upstairs and they look at the entire
building
and they recommend uh
various elements.
Glad to have it. That is not a problem.
We we've gone off into I don't know
where
this has really really become
disturbing to me and particularly when
my name comes up as possible
some explanation of why this
amendment is a good idea.
So I would urge I I that that's not a
problem. It shouldn't be a problem with
anyone in a home business that is
licensed and regulated.
Shouldn't be a problem. It's not a
problem to us. And that is entirely and
completely different
from a residence that does not have a
licensed
uh business in them. When you do, you
take on that responsibility. It's not
difficult.
it is actually helpful. And so I think
that um
I I absolutely speak in opposition to
this. We've reached the point where
we're uh really getting away from the
legal interpretation
into um
something that is frankly irrelevant to
the discussion. We've worked long and
hard on this. Uh, enough's enough.
Please vote no.
>> Anyone else on the governing body?
>> All right. The motion is to define the
area. All those in favor, please signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> Now. All right. Dr. Emmens, Mr. Wolf,
Mr. Crave, myself, Mr. Leborn, Mr.
Escoel, Mr. White, and Dr. Renie Arnos.
this fails and we're back on the
substitute before us.
Anybody else on the governing body on
the substitute?
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Sorry to belver this. Um, I did send an
email out to council um with regard to
sort of a structural issue that I just
wanted to make you aware of. If this is
going to have a reporting requirement in
it and that reporting requirement is
going to be permanent, um I would
recommend that this body move that
reporting requirement into the city code
so that it's permanent and so that
people can access it and so that doesn't
get forgotten. Um, on the other hand, if
the uh if the governing body does not
want that to be a permanent obligation,
um I would recommend that you insert
some sort of sunset date on that
reporting requirement um and leave it as
a non-codified uh section of this
ordinance. Uh however, I I did feel like
I needed to raise that.
>> Thank you, Mr. Brody. Uh we're back on
the substitute. Um any other comments on
the substitute before us?
All right. Hearing none. All those in
favor of the substitute as amended,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed. The substitute is
adopted. And we're back on the main
motion. Comments from members of the
governing body.
>> All right. Hearing none.
>> Hey, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes.
>> I have some comments to make.
[snorts]
>> Mr. Label,
I hope we learned something here.
I know I did.
I've been here a long time.
I've worked with these people who are to
uh act on this ordinance.
And when I look back on the discussion
that we're having, of course, it's
always fascinating and interesting to
discuss the Constitution of the
United States, the state of Wyoming, and
how we
who are sworn to uphold it, interpret
it, and act on it.
[clears throat] Excuse me.
>> [snorts]
>> And it all gets back to the term
reasonable
or unreasonable.
What we've worked on over this period of
time
can only be defined
both legally
and in common usage as reasonable.
because we're reasonable people
and we work with reasonable people here.
And I think that one of the things that
hasn't really come up, but I want to
speak to is who are these individuals
who are going to be enforcing this?
the fire department,
the chief,
they've all served us well in many, many
ways, in many, many times.
Not so long ago, they were out in the
night fighting a uh grass fire.
Sometimes they have to deal with uh
difficult people in difficult situations
and seek the assistance of our police
department.
These are reasonable people doing
reasonable things.
And I think the idea that we would
actually
authorize and encourage the kind of
things that I've heard come up is just
not
in Cheyenne.
There's no doubt that there is
government overreach somewhere
in some things.
We don't deal with that.
We deal with what's here and we deal
with it in a way that and obviously it's
clear there's differences of opinion on
the council. big differences of opinion,
but we support and believe in the
individuals that work for us and we know
them
and we know that they are not the kind
of people that go out and want to go
into someone's home for some
unauthorized purpose. That just is not
happening. It's not going to happen.
It's not part of this.
But what has come to my attention and I
I feel very strongly about Mr. Mayor and
members of the council is abandoned
buildings.
Okay, everybody agrees. I think I
haven't heard anybody suggest that
abandoned buildings weren't a deep
concern,
but it is a expensive concern. It is a
legal concern
and we have a number of abandoned
buildings particularly
uh residences that really require
immediate attention
and I look forward to being able to do
that as we proceed into the budget and
we look at these things. We can't just
leave that house sitting there boarded
up
after it's burned
for who knows who to get back in and do
who knows what. Nothing good ever
happens in an abandoned building.
And I've worked on that with a number of
uh people that are here tonight.
And we need stronger tools to deal with
it. And we need a budget
to deal with those problems in a way
that we have yet to quite accomplish.
Some of them can be flipped. Some of
them can be rehabilitated. I've seen
that happen. Some of them have to be
demolished. That's an expensive process.
So, I hope that we might not have
agreement on some of these matters, but
I hope that we have agreement on uh the
fact that these abandoned properties
have to be dealt with. They cannot just
sit there. Uh and I and it's my hope,
Mr. for mayor, members of the council
that when we get into the budget, when
we proceed here, we're going to take a
stronger approach because that is uh
clearly the will uh of the people that
[clears throat] have come here tonight
or commented.
Um and so I look forward to uh working
on that so that some good can come out
of this. But uh speaking only for
myself,
um I'm proud of what we've done here.
We've listened, we postponed,
we rewrote, and more than anything else,
we have the provision of reporting.
So if this comes to pass and these
individuals have good reason to go to
the court, it comes back to us for us to
discuss and look at and public knowledge
for anyone.
What more accountability could we have?
What more transparency could we have?
Then we're going to know about it. You
can know about it and we can look at the
specifics of that situation if and when
it arises.
So, um
I'm proud of what we've done here. I
think we've come up with and listened to
a variety of uh people. I think some of
these ideas are
uh I don't I'm not worried about any
liability
uh for
listening to the the public,
working to amend this, having a public
meeting.
Uh no, we're all mixed up here.
Some some people are mixed up here.
We're not out to take anyone's rights
away or get in anybody's house. This is
basic health and safety to enforce our
codes for the protection of everybody.
And so I hope that uh
we'll pass this and wait for uh that
occasion if and when there is some use
of this that we'll be notified of and we
can notify the community of the
specifics of that matter. And and I I
again one more time I want to say I
trust these people. I work with these
people.
They are public servants and they do a
good job.
We don't want them out doing anything
that they shouldn't. I don't think they
will.
And I think that it really is
unfortunate that we would come to the
belief that in the city of Cheyenne we
would want to uh
ignore the constitution.
Thank you very much.
Jennifer,
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins, through you. I just want
to first and foremost say thank you to
everyone who has participated in this
process. Um, I think this is really
democracy at work and I think that um
while we may not have the perfect uh
ordinance, um I think that it's come a
long way. I appreciate all the work
that's been done on it. uh by yourself
and by our city attorney and my
colleagues on the council. I'm going to
be voting for this tonight uh because I
believe that we have been successful in
putting in guard rails and um that will
protect and put people's minds at ease.
Um I'm also always hopeful that this is
a a ordinance that we'll never have to
use. It would be nice if uh we never had
to utilize this because we could always
get a hold of homeowners or property
owners or um individuals when there is
an emergency um or after an emergency
has occurred. But we know that that's
not always the case. Um, so I think that
with the reporting that has been
included in this that um, and the
accountability um, with the limited
number of people that are able to
actually use this administrative warrant
and the transparency that we've tried to
um, make part of this ordinance that um,
we've made this the strongest ordinance
that we can make it at this current
time. And um I'm not too proud to say if
it if it's not working, I'm okay with
revisiting this in a couple of years and
we work we go at it again. So, but for
this evening, I'll be voting yes on this
because I believe that we have um
addressed the concerns and put on the
appropriate guard rails in order to make
this um something that works for our
community.
>> Any other comments from the governing
body? I just want to make one. Mr.
Brody, thank you. This was a lot of work
and uh um it was something we had to do
on a short period of time. So just want
to say thank you for that. It was a lot
and u I think the final product has
turned out very nice. Madame clerk,
would you take the vote?
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Um
yeah, I want to say that while I
supported the amendment because I think
it narrows the focus significantly and
is a much better product from where we
started, I am so going to vote no. Mr.
Mayor,
>> Mr. Crave,
>> yes.
>> Mr. White,
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> yes.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> Mayor Collins,
>> yes.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> Mr. Escoel,
>> no.
>> Mr. Lebornne,
>> absolutely.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> no.
>> All right. The ordinance is approved on
third and final reading with Dr. Rainey,
Mr. Esabel, and Mr. Moody voting no.
Number nine, ordinance, third reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, various tracks of land
completely surrounded by current city
limits, Situate and eastern Cheyenne,
generally located south of Story
Boulevard, east of Powder House Road,
north of Del Range Boulevard, and west
of Ridge Road.
>> You know, we're just on our third item,
and we're three hours and 38 minutes
into this meeting. It's not a record,
but we're getting close. Um, this is a
the ninth iteration of our county pocket
goal of annexing all the county pockets
100% surrounded by the city limits. A
total of 26 properties. We'll go out to
the audience to see if anybody wants to
speak to this
>> hearing none. Dr. Emtts.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. comments from
members of the governing body on the
annexations.
>> Quick,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you.
And again, there's been no objections to
this annexation, so that's why I'll be
an I vote. Thank you.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> Madame Clerk, would you take the vote,
please?
>> Mr. Moody,
>> I.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Esabel.
>> I.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Hi.
>> This ordinance is approved on third and
final reading.
>> Number 10. Ordinance third reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne. Establishing the
zoning classifications of AG
agricultural and MR medium density
residential for land annexed to the city
of Cheyenne. Generally located south of
Story Boulevard, east of Powderhouse
Road, north of Del Range Boulevard, and
west of Ridge Road.
>> All right. When you annex a piece of
property, you got to give it a city
zone. And that's exactly what we're
doing here. We try to give it the zone
closest to what is in the county now.
And um so we'll go out to the audience
if anybody wants to talk about the zone
districts proposed by our planning
department.
>> All right. Hearing none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor. The recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. Comments for
members of the governing body on the
zones.
>> Hearing none. Madam Mr. White, did you
>> Oh, no sir.
>> Mr. Thank you,
>> Madame Clerk.
>> Mr. Leburn,
>> I
>> Mr. Moody,
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Esel,
>> I of the established zones are approved
on third and final reading. Number 11,
ordinance third reading, amending 5.7.3
accessory dwelling units of the UN
Cheyenne Unified Development Code to
remove owner occupancy and adjust
parking requirements for accessory
dwellings and making conforming
amendments to the definitions of an
accessory dwelling and semi-attached
dwelling under 1.4.4
descriptions of uses of land and
buildings.
>> All right.
Yes, ma'am.
>> Mr. Sheldon has his hand raised. Mr.
Sheldon,
I have to be faster on that.
>> Yes. Thank you. Alan Sheldon, W 2. I
just want to speak in support of the
proposed amendment to 5.7.3 accessory
dwelling units. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Anybody else in the audience?
>> All right. Hearing none, Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final reading, and I so
move.
>> Second. Seconded by Mr. Moody. Comments
for members of the governing body.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Mr. Mayor. Dr. Renie.
>> Dr. uh Mr. Moody. Go ahead, please. You
were first.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Just
want to thank the planning department,
uh Mr. Bloom, Mr. Lloyd, Mr. White for
all your help. Um definitely appreciate
Habitat for Humanity and the Affordable
Housing Task Force. Let's just move this
on. This fits one of our uh really city
goals. Thank you,
>> Dr. Rainey.
>> Mr. Mayor, I'll be brief. As you all
know, I've spoken against this in the
past. I still think that where I thought
this was a great idea when maybe a young
couple could get into their own home and
have an ADU that they could rent to help
um pay their mortgage with not having
the landowner be present. Now, with it
being two rental units, I think that
we're just going to find that um
you know, people are just going to buy
these up for investments and and use
them as rentals. And I think that'll, as
I said, I don't think that protects our
neighborhoods and leads to little
further deterioration of our
neighborhoods. So, I will be a no.
>> Anyone else from the governing body?
>> All right. Hearing none, Madam Clerk.
>> Mr. Escoel.
>> I. Mr. Leborn.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> I
>> Dr. Renie.
>> No.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> I.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> All right. This ordinance is approved on
third and final reading with Mrs. Renie
and Crave voting no.
>> Number 12. Ordinance, second reading,
creating chapter 8.72, private displays
on public property to prohibit the
unauthorized use of public property for
specified private displays.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience want to speak to this ordinance
on second reading?
>> All right. Hearing none, Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the motion to approve on
second reading failed in the public
service committee. Therefore, there is
no recommendation.
However, however, for the sake of
discussion, I move to approve on second
reading.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White,
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Hello.
>> I'm sorry. There is an a substitute,
I believe, on this item.
>> I'm not aware of one.
>> Pardon me.
>> Um, Mr. Hopinson prepared a substitute
for this item and it was uh I believe it
was given out by
Jennifer earlier this week.
>> No, ma'am.
>> Okay. Well,
then we'll I'll bring the substitute to
the committee meeting next week. Thank
you.
>> Point of order, Mr. Mayor.
>> Dr. any
>> for the council woman from W three. She
if she really has a substitute out
there, she may want to move to postpone
because if it fails tonight, it will not
be heard at committee.
>> I would uh move to postpone.
>> Second.
>> All right, we have a motion to postpone
which would take it to the next meeting
of the governing body. Um, anybody in
the audience? Governing body? Yes,
>> Dr. Amits.
>> Mr. Mayor, I want to speak against this
um this um
>> postponement.
>> Yes, I want to speak sorry, I want to
speak against the postponement.
Um I feel very strongly that this bill
is not necessary at all. Um
I'm gonna try to hold it together here.
>> Okay.
In the library,
at the public library, there's a bench
when you walk in. And over that bench is
a sign that says Ryan Emmens.
That's my son
who died when he was 15.
That bench means a tremendous amount to
me and my family.
And I'm sure that the people at the
library think, gosh, I wish I didn't
have to sweep under that bench or around
that bench or wipe it down at night.
But it's something that keeps
my son's name alive.
Every day, twice a day, I drive by a
memorial on Nationway
that is there for a a woman who was
killed several years ago.
This memorial is immaculately
maintained.
All of the items that are that are for
that
uh memorial are close to the tree in the
dirt. So if someone were to mow around
it,
it would cause no interference.
That's for somebody else's child.
And I'm sure it keeps that child alive
in that family's mind.
I think that this whole idea of saying
that this memorial or these memorials
need to be moved is
totally unnecessary,
hurtful,
and an overreach of government.
We talk about this all the time about
how we're overreaching and we get
accused of this and we're doing the very
same thing right now.
So I would
request I would strongly speak against
the postponement of this and move toward
action on the bill or on the ordinance
tonight. Thank you.
>> Anybody else?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Dr. Rainey.
>> Um
I really feel badly arguing against my
colleague from W two on this one, but
then I want to say that I agree with
her. I voted no on this in committee.
Probably will not vote in favor of it in
the future. However, if one of our
colleagues was working on an amendment
or proposed substitute amendment and
thought it been prepared and for some
reason it hadn't, I think it is only
fair to give them that opportunity. I
think we would all want that. Um that's
why I would argue in for the
postponement.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
Mayor Collins through you. Um I I
understand how sensitive this subject is
and that's why this has been quite
honestly an ordinance that I've been
working on since last November. Um
because I wanted to be able to reach the
family for the young woman um on Nation
Way. Uh this uh the substitute that um
was prepared by Mr. Hopinson and our
city attorney's office addressed some of
the concerns that were brought up at the
committee meeting um last week. Um this
it it only does affect um now it will
the substitute is for signage in the uh
rightway not just on city property. So,
I think that it addresses uh things like
this memorial bench um that uh
Councilwoman Emmens has for uh Ryan, and
I think that um it will resolve some of
the issues that we've had. Um so, I
would encourage you to postpone um and
give me a chance to bring it back to
council u the work that Mr. Hopkins and
I have been working on since November.
Other comments from the governing body?
The motion is to postpone. Mr. Labour.
[clears throat]
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, in this
particular case of what is obviously
uh about as emotional and
meaningful of discussion as you could
have. I I'll I welcome the uh
postponement so that uh we can take a
look at this substitute. I'm
concerned that
our process here is getting more and
more
confusing. I mean, there was we're going
to be a substitute on the warrants.
Didn't happen. But in this case, if we
could make sure that anything that comes
out of the city attorney's office is is
brought before us for action, that'd be
a good thing.
I I would have to say that I did go out
and look at this referenced
memorial and uh have no doubt that it's
very meaningful to the people involved,
but it is in the median [snorts]
and um really is not a place where
anyone should be
walking or being right there by Hot
Springs.
And not too distant from it is a second
memorial.
Um,
and
I guess it's a good thing to be
recognizing the dangers in that area
because
uh we've had a number of fatalities of
pedestrians there and as well as
accidents in vehicles.
So,
I I believe we ought to hear out
whatever changes were made because
um
my opinion
>> [snorts]
>> uh changed when I went to the site and
looked at it closely.
Um and what we're seeing is more and
more of these throughout the community
at various places.
And I definitely think that if there's
[clears throat] such a memorial for a
few days,
um that's one thing, but this is
becoming permanent and is attracting
others.
And I think there are other ways, better
ways to memorialize individuals.
Um plant a tree, a bench,
um all sorts of things. But these get
pretty messy
and I think that uh they don't they
don't really
recognize who that person was.
So I speak in favor of the postponement
so we can take a look at whatever
Councilman Aldrich and the city
attorney's office came up with. Thank
you,
>> Mr. Escoel.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you. Um,
that's probably one of the harder votes
for me tonight. Um,
and I too, you know, my father has a a
memorial in Lion's Park over by the
Botanic Gardens.
And, uh, I think there's a difference
between temporary memorials and and
permanent ones. There's a number of them
on the golf course, too, that of other
gentlemen I've known and ladies. Uh, but
I think if I'd been working on an
ordinance for a number of months,
uh, I would like the opportunity to, um,
bring to the council, the substitute,
uh, because that's been in my
experience in the legislature a couple
times or things I've worked on for a
long time and it just doesn't even get
the light of day because it ends up in
the chairman's top drawer.
But, uh, I think she deserves an
opportunity since the ball got dropped
somewhere along the way with this
substitute to, uh, have that opportunity
to bring it to us.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Um, thank you, Mr. Mayor. I just want
you all to know that that's I'm Don't
worry. I don't want anybody to be ups
think you're upsetting me. It's okay.
Vote the way you want to vote. It's
okay. I'm I'm going to vote no, but
that's how it's okay.
>> Miss Wolf,
>> thank you, Mr. Mayor, and through you
and um and I'm so sorry. Uh Kathy, uh I
missed the discussion. I wasn't able to
attend the public service discussion, so
I really haven't heard the arguments
about this. I and I know there is a uh I
mean, lots of states are dealing with
this. Um and um and it I'm a little
troubled by the fact that there really
isn't any public comment about this. I
would have thought uh other than um
Councilman's uh Emmen's comments that
there might be more
uh discussion. So, um I'm going to vote
uh for the postponement simply because I
think we need uh more time and um and
I'd welcome um to just hear the debate.
Um thank you.
>> We might have outlasted them, sir. They
might have been here for it, but they
couldn't handle us anymore. We're four
hours into this meeting. So, um all
right, we have a motion to postpone.
Anybody else in the governing body would
like to speak to that? Hearing none. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
>> No.
>> Dr. Emmens is a no. The uh item is
postponed till the next meeting.
Number 13, ordinance, first reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for certain land located
north of Prairie Avenue, east of
Powderhouse Road, west of Rutter, and
south of Story Boulevard from AG
Agricultural to NR3 neighborhood
residential high density.
>> We'll send this item to the public
services committee.
Number 14, ordinance first reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
southeast of the intersection of South
Gley Highway and East Dea Lane from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park.
>> We'll send this item to the public
services committee. Number 15, ordinance
first reading, annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, various tracks of
land completely surrounded by current
city limits. Situate in western and
southern Cheyenne, generally located
east of I25, south of the intersection
of Westland Road and Missile Drive,
north of West and East Allison Road, and
east of and adjacent to North College
Drive. Also, public services committee
>> number 16, ordinance, first reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classifications of AG
agricultural, MR, medium density
residential, CB, community business, and
LI, Light Industrial, for land annex to
the city of Cheyenne. Generally located
east of I25, south of the intersection
of Westland Road and Missile Drive,
north of West and East Allison Road, and
east of and adjacent to North College
Drive. We'll refer this item to the
public services committee.
>> Next item is number 19B on page four.
Cooperative agreement between the city
of Cheyenne and Laramie County for
federal project B231031
Cheyenne Streets, US30 Delrange
Boulevard and Whitney Road, Laramie
County.
>> All right. Does anybody in the audience
want to speak to this cooperative
agreement?
>> Hearing none. Mr. Escoel
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation
was reviewed under other items on the
agenda at the February 3rd, 2026 finance
committee meeting. Therefore, provisions
of title two of the city code have been
met.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve in the
amount not to exceed $2,523,500.
And I so move second. Been
>> seconded by Mr. Wolf.
Comments from members of the governing
body on this project. Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
I know the hour is late, but uh perhaps
Mr. Cobb could give us a brief overview
of all that went into this and how long
it took. This is a a major major effort
in East Cheyenne that involves a lot of
moving pieces and uh it really deserving
of a little discussion.
>> Mr. Cobb,
>> mayor, I'd be happy to throw you to
>> cliff version, right?
>> The cliffnotee version. And I even wrote
it down. So, I'd even be specifically
very specific. So, I'd say the
cooperative agreements before you are
part of there's two of them here. This
would be item 19B and then we followed
up with 20B. um is a part of a the
federal project B231031
which included improvements at US
Highway 30, Del Range Boulevard and
Whitney Road. Um
these corridors serve both the city
residents, Laramie County, and other
regional traffic through the area. Um
this is a second of four projects in the
area. The first was referred to earlier
by the gentleman that was here. It was
the Van Beern storm project. This was
phase one. Um this is the second which
includes again what I just described to
you and we have two others that are be
forthcoming including Dell Range
Boulevard from Van Beern to College
Drive and the Summit story boulevard
extension project. So again it's a major
component of of an entire system. Um
it's important to note that the cost
share of both of all these items um
utilize 1% optional specific purpose tax
or the fifth penny as referred to these
agreements and all of the roadway
maintenance and infrastructure projects
that have come before this council
supported by that fifth penny and
they're only possible because of that
voter support. Um, it provides local
funding for implementation and it
assists at the use to leverage millions
of dollars in both state and federal
funding. And in this case, it was
federal funding.
>> Thank you, sir.
Any other questions or comments from
members of the governing body? I hear
none. All those in favor of the
cooperative agreement, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed, the cooperative agreement
is approved.
Number 20B, contract modification number
one to contract 7777 between the city of
Cheyenne and the Wyoming Department of
Transportation for federal project
B231031
Cheyenne Streets, US30 Delrange
Boulevard and Whitney Road, Laramie
County.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience
again. Don, are you here for this one?
>> Yes.
>> Come forward, sir. I'm moving along. You
almost missed. Good job.
>> Okay, I know it's I'm going to keep it
brief for you guys. Okay. I'm just
curious. This is using the 1922 o uh 1%
overage tax. I notice also in there
there's overage taxes from 23 to 26. Um
it's kind of interesting. How much money
is in those funds? And if if it's on a
large amount, why do we need another six
penny sales tax? That's all my question.
>> Okay, your point's been made.
He knows that.
Who else in the audience
hearing? None. Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. Mayor, this item was reviewed under
other items for the agenda at the
February 3rd, 2026 finance committee
meeting. Therefore, provisions of title
two of the city code have been met. Mr.
Mayor, the recommendation of the finance
committee is to approve an amount not to
exceed
$866,248.
And I so move
>> second. Seconded by Mr. Moody.
[clears throat]
Comments from members of the governing
body.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Mayor, everybody's gone, but the
true business we're handling here
tonight is uh coming before us. And uh
the point really that we're need to
emphasize here is that fifth penny. If
we didn't have the fifth penny, uh we
couldn't do these things. is coming up
in November and we really need to uh be
talking about this and talking to the
people that live out there and what has
happened. Cheyenne grew to the east. Um
the roadway system didn't and there's
been a lot of effort and cooperative
effort here uh for very major amounts of
money for us to be able to have uh the
kind of a transportation system that we
need. And obviously this will take care
of uh some uh areas and some lights that
uh
had some very tragic accidents. So um I
speak in favor of this. Thank you. Mr.
Escoel, did you have a comment? I saw
your light on earlier.
>> Nope. Anyone else in the governing body?
>> All right. We have a motion to approve
the contract modification. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The contract modification
is approved.
>> Next item is number 21A on page five.
Consideration of bid number S--8-26
for an agreement between the city of
Cheyenne and Fence Track, Inc. doing
business as Full Tilt Services for the
Dry Creek Restoration Project. Phase
one, Metoand Homes and Henderson Ditches
Project.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience want to speak to these uh
projects on the ditches?
Mr. Escabel, do you have a motion,
please?
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to accept the bid
an amount not to exceed $458,292.50.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Moody. Comments for
members of the governing body. Mr.
Leborn.
>> Mr. Lebornne.
>> Okay. [clears throat] Uh,
>> you asked for it to be taken off. You
should ask. You should speak first.
>> All right. Well, thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Um, not to belabor the point, but uh,
we're stretching our resources here to
deal with something that clearly is a
problem in these particular areas are
some of the worst, but is throughout our
entire drainage system.
I think that uh that this is an
opportunity to discuss a little bit or
at least mention
uh what happens in those channels. Well,
they get clogged. they get overgrown.
They have uh more water coming into them
than they can handle. So, I think it's a
good thing we're doing this. I think
that it's about uh all we're probably
going to do for quite a while. But there
is a reason that we sought and are going
to continue to seek at some point that
storm water fee because
these are essential health and safety.
they are choked and overgrown and they
need this attention. So, I hope we'll
approve that 458,000
which is for two relatively short areas
of a massive system. Thank you,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Just real quick, just want to say this
will definitely benefit my constituents.
So, glad to vote I. Thank you,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Dr. Renie
>> just to channel an old friend and keep
the tradition alive. What are we getting
for the 50 cents?
>> You beat me to it, sir. I was on that
one. Thank you very much.
>> Yes,
>> Dr. Aldridge, you can go aheadu.
I just wanted to um say how much I
appreciate uh engineer Cobb. This has
been a project that I know he has uh
probably funded just because he's tired
of hearing me ask him when it's going to
be done. Um the Henderson drainage has
been brought to our attention by our
constituents in Ward 3 um over the last
two to three years and uh we'll be they
will be celebrating at council and
coffee that this is finally uh in the
bidding process. So appreciate all of
his hard work and our constituents will
be very appreciative. Anyone else in the
governing body?
All right. Hearing none, we have a
motion to consider the bid. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. All right. The bid is
approved. Thank you.
>> Next item is number 21 C, consideration
of bid number, excuse me, S--11-26
for an agreement between the city of
Cheyenne and Miller and Suns
Construction, Inc. for the Parsley
Boulevard Greenway connectors project.
All right, we'll go out to the audience
if I find if they have any greenway
lovers out there. Anybody
hearing none, Mr. Esabel?
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to accept a bid in
an amount not to exceed $228,970.80.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White.
Comments for members of the governing
body. Mr. Leborn.
>> Oh, Mr. Mayor, again,
um I'm trying to make a point here. I'm
not sure if it's going outside this room
very much, but these are the kind of
things that make a big difference in our
greenway system. And this is why we need
that specific purpose tax fund for this
use. Uh this is uh came to pass with the
efforts of the Wyoming Department of
Transportation there replacing the
partially bridge, but when you got off
their project limits, uh you needed we
really needed to connect to the uh
existing system under the WA power line
as well as on the other side. So, um,
and I hope I'm not, uh,
bothering anybody,
but this is something we need to talk
about and point to relentlessly
as we enter into that period of time
looking at that uh, those taxes. Um,
they continue the efforts that we that
are being made. their cooperative
efforts with uh other agencies and they
uh if we don't have that money uh we're
not going to do it and we're going to
have a uh system that is uh deficient
and actually dangerous. So I uh
certainly uh believe that we should pass
this. Thank you.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> Hearing none.
>> Oh, Jennifer, you have a hand raised. Go
ahead. Who is it?
The hand's not raised anymore.
>> All right. I love that. Thank you. Um,
we have a a bid for uh the greenway. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I. Those opposed. This bid is also
approved.
>> Next item is 22A on page six.
Appointment of Rebecca Ogalry to the
community action of Laramie County
Board.
>> All right. As mayor, I don't get to vote
on appointments that I make, but I will
take the vote. Uh looking
>> I would so move
>> moved by Dr. Aldidge seconded by Mr.
Escoel.
All those in favor of the appointment
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The appointment is
approved. We thank her for her service.
>> 22B voucher report.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience or on the governing body that
would like to speak to the vouchers?
>> Hearing none. Next item, please.
Announcement of a public hearing to be
held Monday, February 23rd, 2026 at 6
o'clock p.m. in city council chambers
21101 O'Neal Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming,
and via electronic conference meeting
for renewal applications for existing
city liquor licenses, retail restaurant
limited retail, resort bar and grill
licenses, micro brewery, satellite
distillery, special malt beverage, and
winery permits filed with the city
clerk's office. announcement that due to
the President's Day holiday on Monday,
February 16th, 2026, the regularly
scheduled city council committee
meetings will instead be held in city
council chambers, 21101 O'Neal Avenue,
Cheyenne, Wyoming, and via electron
electronic conference meeting as
follows. Public services committee will
meet Tuesday, February 17th, 2026 at
noon. And finance committee will meet
Wednesday, February 18th, 2026 at noon.
Other business.
>> All right. At this time, we'll open it
up. Is anybody in the audience here to
speak to us under other business? Miss
Whan, are you here to talk to us?
>> I am.
>> Well, thank you for sitting through this
whole meeting. My
>> pleasure.
>> Mayor Collins and council members,
>> tell us who your name is. I know your
>> name is Mary Whan.
>> I'm here to represent myself. I'm a
lifelong resident of Cheyenne. I live in
the county, but I spend a lot of time in
the city.
The first time I addressed city council
was in the 1980s. I wrote a letter to
Virgil Slow asking him to look at the
park, the city park, Lions Park, and I
was noticing that there were a lot of
memorial monuments going up along the
pathway. And I asked him to consider
putting plaques on trees or planting
trees to memorialize people who had lost
their loved ones rather than turning it,
excuse me, [clears throat] turning it
into a like a cemetery. I wanted to keep
it a living park.
So now I'm here to address that same
issue. I'm the daughter of a World War
II Corsair pilot and the sister of two
Vietnam veterans.
I'm here to address something that
caught my eye on the Wyoming Veterans
Commission
website. It's called the Freedom Point,
the living tribute in Lion's Park.
I found that yesterday on the website
and I went to the park today and looked
at the site
and it says it's the future home of the
living tribute in Lion's Park.
So
earlier tonight I looked up how many
months it's been. It's been 10 months
and April 26, 2025
uh city the city of Wyoming and said,
"We're excited to announce plans to
create Freedom Point."
That was 10 months ago. And I went to
the park today and it's still the same
patch of grass with a sign on it. And I
looked up who's going to be honored at
this memorial.
And my concern is that there's an
exclusion
of very many important members of our
community.
My dad went to the World War II monument
in Washington DC with the Honor Flight.
And
by the time he was able to go there, he
wasn't able to see.
He went and enjoyed
all the special treatment that the
veterans got.
And his favorite thing at that memorial
was the little children that came up to
him and gave him flowers
and told him thank you.
I don't think
Well, let me stop there. Um,
I I've read the website there and it
said
some of the comments that you got when
you were anxious about creating this
were, "It's great to have a monument,
but
maybe we should pay more attention to
making our VA look good
or the Buffalo home in Buffalo
or support a group called Veterans
Talking to Veterans and support the
actual living veterans and military in
our community. Thank you,
>> Mary. It's nice to see you. Thanks for
being here tonight. Anybody else in the
audience want to speak to us under other
business?
You had to pick the night we have the
longest meeting of the year.
>> Well, I didn't get a chance last time.
Jim Chiro over on off of 20th Street
there.
>> Can you see your last name again?
>> Chiro, like chiropractor.
um retired Air Force, retired DHS, uh
love Wyoming, bought property way back
in um 2010 out there in medicine bone
that um I really take my hat off to you
guys. I mean, I've been on HOA boards
and that they've never lasted this long.
I mean, some of the some of the stuff
could have, you know, could have been
kind of shoved under the rug. Um, I'm
I'm pleading with you guys because I've
been in Cheyenne um as a resident in the
Cheyenne for about two years now and
I've called numerous times to the
traffic division. I guess Dennis has
already retired. He was real nice. Gave
me a bucket of paint for the yellowing,
you know, by the the curbs and things of
that. Huger and 20th is a huge huge
problem. We I have at least two dozen
children walk across that area. There's
no crosswalk. People think it's a
dragster coming from up there at the top
of the hill where Al's Bar is. When that
light turns green, they're racing 55
miles an hour and even more. My car
recently just got hit by a driver
because of sunlight and that, but the
other issue on 20th, and you can go and
look yourself all the way to 20th, all
the way until you come down to city hall
here, there's no wrongway signs at all.
But 19th has them. If almost every other
intersection, the red signs that say
wrong way or that way, at least twice a
week, whether it's day or night, I see
someone going the wrong way. And it's
not somebody with a Colorado tag either.
A lot of times it's folks that don't
know which way they're going. The
problem what I'm worried about is one of
those kids that are looking up the road
up back up there toward what is it? Um,
Logan. They're looking that way because
it's a one-way street on 20th, but
they're not looking that way. and
another car come the wrong way and it's
it's happened. My truck has even gotten
hit on 20th there because the guy was
blinded by the the sunlight, but that's
a whole another story. But at the very
least, it holds up a little bit more
legality. Could we get a crosswalk put
in there? I mean, I I I even went to the
your your honor, mayor, I even went to
the point of going to a striping company
that does parking lots and that and I
was going to pay the $800 to do it, have
it done myself, just the white lines.
That's all I'm asking for. Then when I
fall back with the city, if I did that,
I would get in trouble for defacing city
property, which oddly enough, I don't
know if we're just out of paint, if you
know, they're just sitting in in the in
their office just drinking too much
coffee and they don't want to go out
there and do it. They do come by when I
call and complain about, you know, doing
the street sweeping because if and I can
show you video. We get heavy rains, all
that water converges and mud right there
at 20th and Huger and then it it floods.
I mean, when we got that big hail storm,
we had 2 feet of water. I've got video I
can show you from when the tractor
trailers are going through and cars
trying to go through that area. I'm not
asking for a major uh expense on the
sewer or the storm drain thing. I'm just
asking for pedestrian sign and do the
white checker marks right there. It'll
help out a little bit more. You know, I
know we only have like one traffic guy
and not expecting someone to sit there
running radar, but we need something.
And and the opposite way, if you look,
19th has almost every other
intersection. The big red sign says
you're going the wrong way. Could we do
something? You know, I said I'd be
willing to pay for it. If the city's
that broke and we can't put a little
paint down, you know, I'm not going to
pay for the signs because that's a
little bit too much. But I think it
would help somebody maybe is
disoriented, you know, comes off a side
road done or um, you know, some other
street and doesn't realize that maybe
they're new into town, they do have a
Wyoming tag and they go the wrong way.
So, I just don't want I don't want a kid
getting hit.
>> Jim, you made your point and the good
part is the people that are responsible
that are in the room. They've heard it.
Uh, I don't think the problem is that we
don't have the paint. think sometimes
the problem is is that uh in order to
have a crosswalk there's warrants that
are that we're required by uh by our
rules to to meet and so we'll check and
see if those warrants are met and if
they are we'll see what we can do and if
they're not u um
>> our chief of police is over there maybe
we can get somebody to stop by and check
on that a little bit for you
>> check on it yeah because I know further
up as you go back up Huger they've got
it closer to the elementary school but
we've got at least two dozen kids and
you know the parents are walking them
our older brother is like a dart across.
I' I've taken pictures. I've taken
video. You know, cars are weaving him
out. One guy was with his walker and the
and the Jeep weaved around him instead
of yielding to him, you know, coming
across that. So, I just [snorts]
appreciate it. You know,
>> appreciate you bringing it to our
attention. Thank you.
>> And thanks for sitting through our whole
meeting.
>> Thank you.
>> Appreciate it.
>> Anybody else?
>> Jennifer.
>> Uh Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Hey, I'm I'm uh Mr. Mr. Mayor, members
of the council, I'm I'm hanging in there
with you. Um, uh, tonight we took a big
step forward by codifying a reporting
requirement for administrative warrants.
That was a win for transparency, and I
want to thank you for that. I'd like to
ask this body to consider replacing that
or I'm sorry, expanding that commitment
to all levels of city governance. Right
now, if a citizen wants to follow what
is happening in our city, they have to
navigate a maze. The agendas, packets,
and minutes for city council, the
planning commission, the board of
adjustment, and various subcommittees
are often scattered across different
pages, released on different schedules,
and buried in complex file structures.
It is currently a full-time job just to
figure out when decisions are being
made, let alone what is being decided.
My request is simple. I ask that the
city explore creating a unified public
access portal, a single consolidated
calendar and document hub where all
public meeting materials are posted in
one place. No more hunting through
different department pages. No more
guessing when a packet will be released.
Just one central location where a
citizen can see the entire schedule of
city governance for the week and access
the relevant documents with one click.
You have an engaged citizenry. We prove
that tonight. Please give us the tools
to stay informed so we can come here and
have productive conversations like the
one we just had. Thank you.
>> Thanks for being sticking with us, Mr.
Miller. Anybody else? Jennifer.
>> All right. Um, I'm going to ask for a
motion. Oh, let's go to the city
council. Does any city council have
things under other business?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. ESL.
>> I just wanted to say that I wanted to
honor my brother tonight. He was a
Vietnam veteran and uh we'll be taking
him out to the veteran cemetery this
Thursday.
Uh
was just a a great guy. He was like a
second father to me. And uh I know I
talked about him about a month or so ago
and uh our family's coming in for it
from all over the country. Thank you.
>> It's a big family. We're going to have
to have a big house to hold them all.
So, thank you, Kim. Anybody else in the
governing body,
>> Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes.
>> I'm sorry. Dr. Aldridge has her hand
raised.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I just wanted to
remind everyone that uh the council and
coffee for ward 3 will be held on
Saturday, February 21st from 9 through
11 at Dosbog located at College in
Persian. And so we would love to see
folks come out and visit with us uh
regardless of what ward you live in.
>> Anyone else? All right, Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. Mayor, pursuant to Wyoming statute
section 164405,
I move that the governing body meet in
executive session to consider or receive
any information classified as
confidential by law.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we have a motion by Mr. Crave,
seconded by Mr. Moody that we move into
executive session. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right, the motion is passed. Just
for people online and and uh in uh the
audience, we are going to go into
executive session, but when we're done,
we are going to u just adjourn the
meeting. There'll be no other business
at the governing body. So, with that,
we'll turn off all the electronics and
ask everyone who doesn't have part of
that executive session to leave us.
No, when I was